<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-14T16:57:15+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andrei Guevorkian</title><subtitle>Personal Portfolio and Blog.</subtitle><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><entry><title type="html">Through the Ruins of Western Armenia</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/trip-to-turkey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Through the Ruins of Western Armenia" /><published>2025-08-01T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/trip-to-turkey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/trip-to-turkey/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-im-writing-this&quot;&gt;Why I’m Writing This&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I want to acknowledge something. What we saw on this trip will not last forever. If my great grandchildren visit eastern Turkey, they will find fewer traces of a past armenian presence than we did. The ruins will be fewer, the outlines fainter, and the carvings thinner. And some places will be completely gone. What can still be touched today may one day exist only in photographs and in the words of those who took the time to record it. An example of this is city names. &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(Note 1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is one reason I am writing this. Documenting this trip is a small form of preservation. And for the (over) 95% of Armenians from the diaspora who will never set foot in the villages their great grandparents fled from, all they have are stories like these. For them, these places exist only in black and white photographs and in documentaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not from these towns myself, but my friends are. And so we decided to go see them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THe purpose of this trip was to see everything armenian. To see what the armenians have built, as well as the nature that they have seen. If there was beautiful nature along the way, we’d stop. If there was a beautiful mosque along the way, we’d stop. Because Turkey has a beautiful culture, despite … (their denial, their dark past around which they (change)). …!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-turkey-does-not-show-you&quot;&gt;What Turkey Does Not Show You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, something I learned firsthand during this trip, is that Turkey does not invite you to notice the Armenian past. Often, all we had were Google Maps pins to follow, leading us to seemingly random places that felt like they were waiting to be repurposed or erased (probably through abandonment/neglect).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signs point elsewhere, museums and official placards mention other empires, and any link with Armenians is conveniently omitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fallen church is not just stones on the ground. It is a witness that can no longer testify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without these tangible reminders, the story of Armenians in these lands will rely more on written records and memory, both of which are easier to ignore and forget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;beginning-our-trip&quot;&gt;Beginning our Trip&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ani&quot;&gt;Ani&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you haven’t seen the Falcon Heavy, STOP READING and WATCH THIS.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/A0FZIwabctw&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.teslarati.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/Falcon-Heavy-B1052-B1053-LZ-landing-SpaceX-1-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;testhere&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/A0FZIwabctw&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Click here or the image above to be redirected to the Youtube video!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;test1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://youtu.be/A0FZIwabctw&quot; title=&quot;Akhtamar boat ride&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;test&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;responsive-video-container&quot;&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/A0FZIwabctw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;test short&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;responsive-video-container&quot;&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/bAtqSc2y-wY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny/sad because I name other places by their Turkish names followed by the Armenian names. And this would’ve happened here if the Turkish government would change the name Ani to Anı (pronunciation changes), which they apparently did consider/attempt doing. They would’ve said that “anı” means “memory” in Turkish, which would give it a symbolic undertone. But thankfully the name Ani is too entrenched in history. At this point it would draw too much negative attention to Turkey and would bring to light all the Turkification it has done to Armenian sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ani was built during the era of Bagratid Armenia (885–1045 AD). Bagratid Armenia was a medieval Armenian kingdom founded by Ashot I Bagratuni, and it marked the first independent Armenian state after centuries of foreign rule (mostly Arab and Byzantine domination). Its capital moved around, but in 961 AD, Ani became the capital. Take a moment to look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_capitals_of_Armenia&quot;&gt;this very important and informative link of capitals of various Armenian kingdoms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ani#/media/File:Bagratuni_Armenia_1000-en.svg&quot;&gt;At its peak&lt;/a&gt;, Ani had potentially 100’000 inhabitants, rivaling Constantinople and Baghdad in beauty and wealth. At this point I should note also that although it is named “the city of 1001 churches”, it didn’t actually have that many. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ani&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; has it, “to date, 50 churches, 33 cave chapels and 20 chapels have been excavated by archaeologists and historians.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1045 AD, Ani was surrendered without much resistance to the Byzantine Empire, who wanted this front to defend against the Seljuks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1064 AD however, the Seljuks captured Ani and many inhabitants were killed or enslaved, and much of the city was destroyed. This was the start of the decline of Ani. (This conquest played a significant role in the movement of Armenian into Cilicia, which was officially established as a principality in 1080 AD, and was a full-on kingdom between 1198 and 1375.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in 1072 the Shaddadids (a Mulsim Kurdish dynasty) bought Ani from the Seljuks. They ruled until 1199, so a lot of intermarriages occurred all throughout historic Armenia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, the Georgians took control, and encouraged Armenians to settle back. They even let Armenian nobles rule (Zakarid princes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it all came down in 1236 AD after the Mongols entered Ani during their expansion into the Caucasus. Unlike the Seljuk’s, who massacred tens of thousands, Mongols often took cities for taxation. To be exact, they stormed Ani, killed many defenders, and looted churches and homes. Then, they imposed heavy taxes on the survivors instead of wiping the city out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city faced further damage from a significant earthquake in 1319, which further contributed to its decline. By the 15th–17th centuries, Ani was largely abandoned. Small Kurdish, Persian, and Turkish communities lived among the ruins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we see there today? The most significant is the Cathedral of Ani,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-trajectory&quot;&gt;The Trajectory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, keep in mind this map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/Armenians_in_the_Ottoman_Empire_(1870s).png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of Armenians in Ottoman Empire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you will&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/maps/gyumri-kars.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Gyumri to Kars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were picked up by our driver Tigran at 4:30AM from Gyumri, and got to the Turkish border at 7AM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went through the armenian portion of Georgia, and I’ll go on a little tangent about the Armenian portion of Georgia. &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(Note 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we passed the Turkish border, we then called our taxi contact in Turkey, and left the border at 8AM (time zone shifts by an hour in Turkey). Anyway, we got to the Kars airport at 9AM (GMT+03:00), and waited until 10:30AM for Avis (car rental company) to give us our car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/maps/kars-van.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Kars to Ani to Van&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:30AM we head to Ani, walk around for 3 hours (bring some water with you), and head toward Van.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I highly recommend doing what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b3cJGvvnraU&amp;amp;list=PLcvSvkQpP-ACKxrp15AMdBDOT3BDUy36A&amp;amp;index=11&amp;amp;t=537&quot;&gt;these guys did&lt;/a&gt;, and that’s go to check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://artofwayfaring.com/destinations/khtzkonk-beskilise-monastery/&quot;&gt;this church&lt;/a&gt; on the way to Van. Just be safe out there when hiking mountains, always be prepared for snakes or wild animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/besh-kilise.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Besh Kilise&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another note on the way to Van is, I didn’t really appreciate it in the moment, but the view of mount Ararat is the best from the city of Iğdır. Because you think that it’ll get better, and you want to get behind Sis and Masis, but the behind is hidden by other mountains. So take a stop at/near Iğdır to look at Masis (the bigger of the two mountains).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/mt-ararat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mt Ararat from Igdir&quot; /&gt;
Source: [https://ku.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/W%C3%AAne:I%C4%9Fd%C4%B1r_ve_A%C4%9Fr%C4%B1_Da%C4%9F%C4%B1.jpg]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While staying in Van, we visited the island of Akhtamar, …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When visiting Akhtamar, we had these churches on our list but I guess we spent too much time in Akhtamar, since we spontaneously decided to swim there after seeing others doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/maps/churches%20in%20van%20region.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Churches we were supposed to see&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You feel extremely greasy from the lake, and at first we thought it’s because they dump some industrial waste into the water or something, but turns out that that is the natural chemical composition of that lake. It’s what is known as a soda lake, which is any lake with a pH of between 9 and 12. It’s just rich in particular salts which makes the water highly alkaline (Lake Van has a pH of 9.7), and when our skins touches these salts, and leaves a soapy feeling. As long as you don’t have any cuts on your skin, and you shower afterwards, there is no problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun I checked what would happen if you were to drink the water from Lake Van. If you take a few sips, your stomach acid (pH ~ 1.5-3.5) would immediately neutralize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/maps/van-elazig.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Van to Elazig trip&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitlis
Muş
Yukarıyongalı&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent two nights in Van, and headed towards Elazig, where we had the hotel booked for one night. On the way there we stopped at Mush, and a small village called Yukariyongali. We drove past the lake XYZ, where tens of thousands of armenians were killed during the genocide, It was a top 3 killing ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, from Elazig we drove t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cappadocia&quot;&gt;Cappadocia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect many people to know this, but Cappadocia was once inhabited by Armenians. I learned this during the trip itself when I started to zoom into Cappadocia on Google Maps, and started to notice churches. These were not Armenian churches, bu&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in 1021, the last king of Vaspurakan, Gagik Artsruni, handed the kingdom over to the Byzantine Empire in exchange for land in Cappadocia, due to pressure from Turkish invasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;erzurum-and-the-case-of-the-armenian-turkish-relations-library&quot;&gt;Erzurum and the case of the Armenian-Turkish relations library&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We weren’t prepared to debate, but next time I’d like to keep the following ideas in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have Armenians ever lived in Nakhichevan. How were there khachkars then in Jugha? Do you think it was right to destroy them? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-potential-future-trip&quot;&gt;A Potential Future Trip&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at this map again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/Armenians_in_the_Ottoman_Empire_(1870s).png&quot; alt=&quot;Map of Armenians in Ottoman Empire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re goal is this follow “Armenianess”, well then it’s quite obvious that the southern portion is where you’d want to be. Going all to way to Adana, visiting Batman, Diyarbakır (Tigranakert), Mardin, Şanlıurfa (Urfa), Gaziantep and much more (which I’d have to research about) along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another potentially interesting trip could include traveling closer to the northern coastline of Turkey. The Hemshin Muslims in Rize (through Artvin I imagine) are an interesting group to visit as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about names of cities. An obvious example to begin with is Istanbul, which used to be Constantinople, the City of (Roman Emperor) Constantine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 285 CE, the Roman Empire was divided in two for easier rule: one emperor in the East and one in the West. The Eastern Roman Empire became what we later call the Byzantine Empire, with Constantinople as its capital (named after Emperor Constantine in 330 CE). The Western Roman Empire collapsed in 476 CE, while the Eastern half survived another thousand years until it was captured by the Ottomans in 1453.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greeks have always referred to Constantinople as “the city”, and they have continued doing so when the Turks arrived. Over time, the Turks have heard countless times the phrase “εἰς τὴν Πόλιν” (“is tin pólin”) which means “to the city” in Ancient Greek. In turkish pronunciation, that became Istanbul. By the nineteenth century, “Istanbul” was already widely used among Turks, while “Constantinople” remained in foreign and official documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fall of the Ottoman Empire in 1922, the new leader, Mustafa Kemal Atatürk carried out a wide set of modernization reforms. One of them was language reform. The Arabic script was abandoned and a Latin alphabet was introduced in 1928. Alongside this came the standardization of place names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1930 the Turkish government formally asked the international community to use “Istanbul” instead of “Constantinople.” This was done through an official notice to foreign governments, embassies, and international postal services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so that is the story of Istanbul. We could say this was a fairly natural change of names. The word Istanbul grew out of everyday speech, and Turks had already been using it for centuries. The government’s request in 1930 only made the rest of the world follow suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all name changes in Turkey happened so naturally. Under Sultan Abdul Hamid II in 1880, even the word “Armenia” was banned from schools, newspapers, and official records. The first name changes started when, in 1916, the minister of war, Enver Pasha, ordered that towns, villages, rivers, and mountains with Armenian, Greek, or Bulgarian names be replaced with Turkish ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Turkish Republic was founded in 1923, Mustafa Kemal Atatürk’s reforms continued the process. He even banned imported maps and non-Turkish street names in Istanbul were changed by 1927. In 1952, the Special Commission for Name Change was created and went on to change tens of thousands of names across the country. Mountains, rivers, streets, monuments, quarters and neighborhoods. Not to mention villages, towns and cities. And it’s not just Armenian names of course. That geographic location is full of history, contributed by countless ethnic groups, including other muslim groups. It is agreed upon that thousands of Armenian, Greek, Kurdish, Arabic, Georgian, and Assyrian place names were officially changed over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kurds and other Muslim minorities were mostly exempt from name changes during the Ottoman Empire because the state presented itself as an Islamic caliphate (which just means that its led by a caliph, the successor of the Prophet Muhammad and the leader of all Muslims). But after the Ottoman Empire collapsed, and after Armenians and Greeks were eliminated, the pressure turned on them as well. During the genocide, many Kurdish tribes were promised land and property in return for helping in the massacres and deportations. Some benefited for a time, but once the new, secular and modern Turkish Republic was born, they too faced assimilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of the name changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Armenian island of Aghtamar (about the legend of Princess Tamar) became Akdamar (white vein).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dikranagert (named after king Tigran), in 1937, was made into “Diyarbakır” (“land of copper” in Turkish). By the way, this city was known as “Amed” by Kurds and Assyrians. There is also claim that it used to be called “Diyar Bakr”, meaning “land of the Bakr tribe,” used by Arabs from early medieval times. So Diyarbakır could just be its reinterpretation of that (nonetheless, they gave it a new meaning).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karin became Erzurum, which comes from Arabic Arz al-Rum (land of the Romans).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sepastia became Sivas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kharpert became Harput, and the new city of Elazığ was built next to it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Erznka became Erzincan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mount Masis, also known as Ararat, became Ağrı.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ancient city known to Greeks as Smyrna (destroyed in 1922) was renamed Izmir (again,  foreign governments were asked to adopt this new Turkish name).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Georgian town of Vitz’e renamed to Fındıklı (“place with hazelnuts” in Turkish).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reinforce this knowledge, you can see some of these here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/Armenian%20city%20names.png&quot; alt=&quot;Old Armenian city names&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/ATD_of_the_regions_of_Turkey_occupied_by_Russian_troops_during_WW1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Old Armenian city names&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as you can see, sometimes they tried to find similar words that meant something in Turkish, and make it seem like it was a gradual and natural change in language, adopted by the inhabitants. But in reality, it’s been ordered one day to change. They tweak the sound and spelling into a Turkish form, keeping it recognizable and Turkifying it at the same time. The old identity gets quietly phased out, and over time, younger generations grow up thinking the Turkish form was the real name all along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you scroll down to the various maps &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/articles/Place_name_changes_in_Turkey#Greek&quot;&gt;on this website&lt;/a&gt;, you will see which ethnicities lived where in Turkey. I highly encourage a quick look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what about a place like Van? Van stayed Van, probably because Van was so ancient and tied to the ancient kingdom of Urartu, which Turks don’t even believe are related to modern Armenians. And something like Nakhichevan? Nakhijevan means “first resting place” in Armenian, as it is thought that after landing on Mount Ararat, Noah first settled in the Nakhijevan area. Nakhichevan is one of the oldest continuously inhabited places in the region, mentioned by Greek, Persian, Armenian, and Arab historians for over two thousand years. So changing it outright would be a bit awkward, and what the Turks/Azeris say instead is that it’s of ancient Turkic origin (Naxçıvan), rather than Armenian. And so they can say that, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian_cemetery_in_Julfa&quot;&gt;destroy the tens of thousands of Armenian artifacts&lt;/a&gt;, and claim continuity of their rule over that land. Unfortunately for them, this part of history is recent enough that it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.archaeology.org/online/features/djulfa/&quot;&gt;well documented from outside sources&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last point I’ll mention is that many of these places were called differently by the various minorities present in the region, such as Dikranagert/Amed. But the point is that these names were passed down through generations of natives and bear thousands of years of history, while the new name (Diyarbakir) was made up by a committee in an office to obscure history and attempt to cover up a century of ethnic cleansing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renaming a place is the last step of a cycle that’s happening even today. Azerbaijan recently captured the Armenian territory of Artsakh, and they will now make sure that everybody follows suit with their names. Google Maps used to have Stepanakert, capital of Artsakh, but now it only has Khankendi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Destroy, erase, rename, repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-im-writing-this&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region called Javakheti, in Georgia, is majority Armenian (50%+). Towns like Akhalkalaki and Ninotsminda are 95%+ Armenian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/Ethnic-Armenians-in-Georgia-Map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Armenian population in Georgia&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That region has been historically Armenian for centuries. It was part of many Armenian kingdoms (I’m not good at this but it can be traced back to the Urartians from the 9th–6th century BCE. And if you don’t consider the Urartians as Armenians, then there’s the Orontid Dynasty, which is considered the first Armenian dynasty, from the 6th–2nd century BCE). So ever since then, there were Armenians living in those lands; throughout Mongol, Persian, Ottoman, and finally Russian rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially after the 1828 Russo-Turkish War, when the Russians took the territory from the Ottomans, many Armenians fled the Ottoman Empire into that region, and settled there permanently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 1917, when the Russian Empire collapsed. At that point, this was the map of the Russian Empire:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/turkey/Russian-expansion-Asia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Russian Empire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgia declared its independence on May 26, 1918, and the First Republic of Armenia declared it on May 28, 1918.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javakheti’s population was overwhelmingly Armenian at that point, but when the Russian forces retreated, Georgian troops swiftly went in and took control. The Armenian locals weren’t happy, but Armenia couldn’t do anything about it; it was busy fighting the Ottoman invasion of May–June 1918 (which included the famous Battle of Sardarabad in May 21-29). If Armenia had lost that battle, there may not have been an Armenia at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Georgia in a way took advantage of that situation, and also ended up taking the region of Lori (they claimed that region based on the fact that it was part of the georgian Kingdom of Kartli-Kakheti, which existed before the Russian annexation, from 1762 to 1801). In December 1918, there was a short “war” for Lori and Javakheti regions (both of which had Armenian-majority populations.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Javakheti region was actually included in the Armenian proposals for the Treaty of Sevres of 1920, but since the purpose of the treaty was to split up the Ottoman Empire, and Javakheti was part of the former Russian Empire, that claim was ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, in 1920-1921, the Red Army invaded both countries, and now it was the ultimate time to decide who gets what. We know Karabakh was given to the Azerbaijanis, and we also know that Javakheti belongs to Georgia today, and Lori belongs to Armenia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did the Soviets give Javakheti to the Georgian SSR? Well, one reason is that before the Russian Empire annexed Georgia, that land did belong to the Georgian Kingdom of Kartli-Kakheti. Secondly, just like with Karabakh, the Soviets wanted to intentionally mix ethnic groups across internal republic borders (a classic imperial tactic used to prevent unified nationalism and to create dependence on central authority). Thirdly, and probably most importantly, the Georgian SSR was a larger republic, with more resources, access to the Black Sea, and natural mountain barriers separating it from the Ottomans. So giving Javakheti to Georgia was a strategic move by the Soviets to secure loyalty from the Georgians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-trajectory&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="History" /><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html">Why I’m Writing This</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Influence of Lobby Groups in the US</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/aipac/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Influence of Lobby Groups in the US" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/aipac</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/aipac/">&lt;p&gt;So I was writing this as a “side note” in the article of “Naked Econ Summary Part 3”, specifically after Chapter 8, but it got way too long, and so I put this in a separate article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-personal-side-note&quot;&gt;A Personal Side Note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, any conversation about political influence has to include AIPAC (the American Israel Public Affairs Committee), the Israeli lobby. I don’t know much about politics, but we always hear about how strong the Israeli lobby is in the US. I want to learn more about why that is, and this section is my (extremely shallow) attempt to better understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, in November 2024, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/unispal/document/the-right-of-the-palestinian-people-to-self-determination-08nov24/&quot;&gt;United Nations held a vote amongst member states asking if Palestinian people have the right to self-determination&lt;/a&gt;. Israel, the US, Paraguay and Argentina were basically the only countries that voted against it. So something is clearly wrong with these countries, and we’ll just take a look at the US in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-history&quot;&gt;Some history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy history, and I do not claim to know the full story with all its intricate details. But here are a few things I find interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Israel was declared a country on May 14, 1948. President Truman officially recognized Israel just 11 minutes after its declaration of independence, making the US the first country to do so. (For context, the Soviet Union recognized Israel three days later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1948, immediately after Israel’s founding, neighboring Arab nations, including Egypt, Jordan, Syria, Iraq, and Lebanon, declared war on Israel. This was the first Arab-Israeli war, during which Israel managed to not only survive but expand its territory beyond the initial borders set by the United Nations partition plan in 1947.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 1955: Egypt, under President Gamal Nasser, began purchasing weapons from the Soviet Union, effectively aligning itself with the USSR during the Cold War. This move set the stage for the second Arab-Israeli war in 1956. That year, Nasser nationalized the Suez Canal, meaning he took it out of private (mostly British and French) control and placed it under Egypt’s government. This led to a conflict involving Israel, Britain, and France against Egypt. Which just in and of itself was an interesting period, because it was a clear indicator of the decline of British and French influence in the world stage (Egypt came out victorious).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three attacking countries had clear motives for their actions. France and Britain were furious about losing control of the Suez Canal, which they saw as crucial to their economic interests and global power. France had additional reasons to oppose Nasser, as Egypt was actively supporting independence fighters in Algeria, then still a French colony. Israel, meanwhile, was increasingly worried about Egypt’s military buildup and its blockade of Israeli shipping through the Straits of Tiran. The three nations planned their attack in secret, with Israel launching the initial invasion while Britain and France joined later under the pretense of separating the warring parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US position was particularly interesting, as they actively opposed their traditional allies. President Eisenhower saw the attack as dangerous old-style colonialism that risked pushing Arab states toward the Soviet Union. The US was also deeply concerned about Soviet threats to intervene on Egypt’s behalf, which could have escalated into a much larger conflict. America went as far as threatening economic sanctions against Britain to force a withdrawal, demonstrating how dramatically global power dynamics had shifted since World War II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this period, Israel began to be seen as a pro-Western ally, while Egypt and other Arab nations increasingly aligned with the Soviet Union. Israel’s relationship with the US started to solidify, especially as tensions in the region grew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1962, under President John F. Kennedy, the US agreed to sell weapons to Israel for the first time. This marked the beginning of a close military partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came the Six-Day War of 1967.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Six-Day War became a major turning point. Israel launched a preemptive strike &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(Note on what led to this)&lt;/a&gt; against Egypt, Jordan, and Syria, capturing significant territories: the Sinai Peninsula and Gaza Strip from Egypt, the West Bank and East Jerusalem from Jordan, and the Golan Heights from Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory demonstrated Israel’s military capabilities and intelligence-gathering expertise, which the US saw as strategically valuable during the Cold War. Israel became a key ally in the region, providing the US with reconnaissance and intelligence while countering Soviet influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what does Israel get in return? Lots of money. From 1946 to 2023, Israel has received an estimated $260 billion in aid from the US. Initially, this included both economic and military aid, but since 2008, the aid has been exclusively military. Israel currently receives $3.8 billion annually as part of a 10-year agreement signed by President Obama in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about the money provided is that Israel must spend most of it in the US. Buying their missile defense systems, their fighter jets, etc. This means the funds flow back into the US economy, benefiting American defense contractors and maintaining US jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to note is that the US has this thing called the Leahy Law, which says that US military hardware can only be used for defensive purposes, and can’t be used in violation of human rights standards. However, these restrictions have never been enforced with Israel, giving them what some describe as a blank check for military operations. Israel is often considered an exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-minor-details&quot;&gt;Some minor details&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While on this topic, I would like to note one thing that I’ve never heard each side never talk about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;palestinians&quot;&gt;Palestinians&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the Palestinians. I first learned about this in the context of the Lebanese Civil War (1975-1990). There were many factors at play, and I am not a historian, but it seems to me that Lebanon already had a fragile social and political order before the arrival of the palestinians and the PLO (Palestinian Liberation Organization). But it was especially when the PLO moved its headquarters to Lebanon in 1970 that tensions escalated (I will soon talk about where they moved from).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lebanon was divided into many different religious groups, including Christians, Sunni Muslims, Shia Muslims, and Druze. Its political system was based on a delicate balance among these groups, determined by demographics. The last official census, conducted in 1932, showed that Christians were 51% of the population. This census heavily influenced how government positions were distributed. However, the influx of hundreds of thousands of Palestinian refugees disrupted this delicate balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it would be unfair to blame the Palestinians alone for the civil war. There were numerous variables at play, including interference from larger regional and global powers. Countries like Egypt, Syria, Iran, the United States, Saudi Arabia, and the Soviet Union had a hand in supporting different factions within Lebanon. The influx of Palestinian refugees, along with the presence of armed PLO militants, became one of the many pressures pushing the fragile system toward collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This topic led me to broader questions, like: “Why doesn’t Egypt take in Palestinian refugees?” There are numerous reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key factor is that Hamas, the governing authority in Gaza, is ideologically aligned with the Muslim Brotherhood. The Muslim Brotherhood is an Islamist organization founded in Egypt in 1928 that advocates for governance based on Islamic principles and opposes secular political systems. They gained significant political power in Egypt after the Arab Spring, briefly ruling the country from 2012 to 2013. However, the Egyptian military overthrew them in a coup and installed President Abdel Fattah el-Sisi (who is president there to this day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El-Sisi supports a secular government model and views the Brotherhood as a major threat to Egypt’s stability. Allowing an influx of Palestinians with potential ties or sympathies toward Hamas could risk introducing another destabilizing element to Egypt’s political landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I stumbled upon a video showing the challenges Palestinian refugees have posed to previous host countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Six-Day War in 1967, many Palestinians fled to neighboring Jordan. The PLO, operating in Jordan, openly opposed the Jordanian monarchy. PLO militants had their own army and even attempted to assassinate King Hussein of Jordan &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(Note 2)&lt;/a&gt;. They also carried out robberies in Amman, targeting families and businesses in the name of collecting “financial assistance” in the ongoing war of attrition against Israel. When the Jordanian police and army tried to protect its citizens from these attacks, they’d get attacked and killed. By 1970, the situation escalated into a civil war, known as Black September, which ended with the expulsion of the PLO from Jordan. On their way out, in 1971, the prime minister of Jordan was assassinated by the Palestinian militant organization known as Black September Organization (BSO). The PLO then moved into southern Lebanon, contributing to the instability there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1991, after the First Gulf War, Kuwait expelled 300’000 Palestinians, which made up 18% of its population. The reason? The PLO supported the enemy, Saddam Hussein, during Iraq’s invasion of Kuwait. And why did the PLO support the attacker of a country which brought them in when they were displaced? Several reasons, but before we get into them, we have to understand the political landscape at the time and the deep-rooted frustrations of the Palestinian people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story goes back to the 1930s when American oil companies first struck massive oil reserves in Saudi Arabia. Standard Oil of California, which later became Chevron, formed Aramco (the Arabian-American Oil Company) and started pumping billions of barrels of oil out of the region. The relationship became formal when President Roosevelt met Saudi Arabia’s King Abdulaziz in 1945, cementing a long-term alliance between the two countries based largely on oil and mutual security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kuwait came into the picture later. It was under British control until 1961, but American oil companies had already gotten a piece of the pie by the 1950s. Gulf Oil and BP were running operations in Kuwait’s oil fields, making the tiny country a strategic partner for the US. By 1990, Kuwait and Saudi Arabia together controlled a huge portion of the world’s oil supply, and the US had serious reasons to protect them from any threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Saddam invaded Kuwait in 1990, the US stepped in for several reasons. First was oil security. If Saddam controlled Kuwait, he would have had enormous influence over global oil prices. Next was regional stability. Letting Iraq get away with annexing Kuwait would have set a dangerous example and made Saudi Arabia a likely next target. There were also defense commitments. The US had promised to protect Kuwait and Saudi Arabia as part of its Gulf security strategy. And then there was credibility. If America didn’t act, its reputation as a reliable security partner would have taken a major hit, possibly driving Gulf states to seek alliances with other powers like the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let me explain why the Palestinians sided with Saddam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First was their deep frustration with the US-backed status quo in the region. Many Palestinians saw America’s strong support for Israel as blocking their aspirations for statehood. When Saddam challenged US power in the region, many Palestinians viewed him as standing up to a system they felt was unfair to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Saddam Hussein had positioned himself as a champion of the Palestinian cause. He explicitly linked his invasion of Kuwait to the Palestinian issue, saying he would withdraw from Kuwait if Israel withdrew from occupied territories. He also launched Scud missiles at Israel during the war, which, while militarily ineffective, was symbolically powerful for many Palestinians who felt powerless against Israel. I also heard that he did so in order to get Israel to attack right back, thus getting muslim-majority countries to side with Iraq. (Israel smartly did not respond to these attacks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, Saddam had provided significant financial support to Palestinian families, particularly families of those killed in conflicts with Israel. This direct aid created goodwill among many Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for the Palestinians, the US came in and completely obliterated Saddam Hussein; once the ground assault began (i.e. troops came in by foot and tanks), Operation Desert Storm lasted 100 hours (I’m trying to say that it was an easy war for the US, and they got to show off their strength). The PLO’s gamble did not pay off, and so they were expelled from Kuwait once the war ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now of course, someone might argue, &lt;em&gt;“If Israel had never been created, none of this would have happened. Lebanon would still be the ‘Paris of the Middle East’, as it was in the 1960s, and Arab nations would be more united”&lt;/em&gt;. I can see that perspective. I also get where the Palestinians were coming from. The PLO felt abandoned by Arab governments that weren’t giving them the support they expected, so they believed they had to force change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, now that the dust has settled, it does look like a classic case of “biting the hand that feeds you”, and so now Egypt has even built a wall to separate itself from Gaza, unwilling to open its borders because it knows taking in more Palestinians would only invite trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like many things involving humans, this is a complex system with countless variables, some big and some small. Israel and the US are big ones. Arab countries siding with them are big ones too, though they had to make tough choices (complex systems in and of themselves). They had to pick a side, and something tells me it’s not exactly fun being an enemy of the US. Then there’s the fact that Hamas leaders live in luxury in Doha, reportedly worth billions, while ordinary Palestinians continue to suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally and most importantly,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advocating for Palestinian statehood is not antisemitic, but wanting Jews to die is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;israel&quot;&gt;Israel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to Israel. In the battle of who is the lesser evil, I think Israel isn’t looking too good. We could ask ourselves “Well what if Gaza never armed themselves, didn’t resist, etc. Wouldn’t they be prosperous right now?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t need to speculate what would happen, because we already know exactly what would happen. The West Bank would happen, but in Gaza. [give history, that palestinians there gave up their weapons, and now its apartheid regime, with settlements being built (explain what are settlements and why its wrong), checkpoints for palestinians, routes are reconfigured for them so they drive around the settlements, which makes their routes longer. All inconvenience for palestinians, on their own land.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Israel is the powerful side here, make no mistake about it. If they want to end the war, they can. Palestinians cannot do anything, they are helpless. It’s Israel who has to somehow step up and propose a solution. But instead, they are doing things to aggravate the situation further. Israel’s actions are what stand between Palestinians and peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-lobbying-just-legalized-bribery&quot;&gt;Is Lobbying Just Legalized Bribery?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a crazy tangent, but back to AIPAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a quote I’ve come across before: “Lobbying is basically legalized bribery”. And yeah, in practice, that is how things work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lobbying itself is not inherently bad. At its core, lobbying is a way for people, organizations, or industries to advocate for policies they care about. It is a legitimate part of democracy that allows citizens and interest groups to communicate their needs to lawmakers. Think about environmental groups pushing for clean energy policies, public health organizations lobbying for more funding, or nonprofits advocating for marginalized communities. These are all examples of lobbying in its ideal form, where it is simply about informing and persuading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem arises when money enters the picture. When you see corporations or powerful groups spending millions of dollars to influence politicians, the entire landscape changes; those with the deepest pockets now have the loudest voices. Politicians rely heavily on campaign contributions to get elected, and donors often expect some kind of return on their investment. And this is where the line between lobbying and bribery begins to blur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a large corporation might lobby for favorable tax policies, and in return, it funds a politician’s campaign. While nothing illegal is technically happening, the exchange creates this environment where politicians prioritize the interests of big donors over the public good. And these well-funded lobbying groups can afford to hire skilled professionals, set up meetings and events to sway politicians. Meanwhile, smaller groups or average citizens often do not have the resources to compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to speak specifically about AIPAC. It was founded in 1951, a few years after the creation of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIPAC operates by focusing on relationship-building and lobbying efforts. It organizes conferences, meetings, and trips to Israel for US politicians to showcase Israel’s strategic importance. These trips are often all-expenses-paid and are designed to leave a positive impression on lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Politicians who align with AIPAC’s agenda can expect significant financial backing. For example, in 2022, AIPAC spent $30m, and these funds were used to support candidates who shared AIPAC’s views on maintaining strong US-Israel ties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, AIPAC educates its members (of which there are tens of thousands of) on how to engage with their local representatives. They help coordinate letters, calls, and visits to push specific policies. The organization also provides talking points and policy briefs that members can share with lawmakers, making it easy for politicians to align with their positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For comparison on the numbers, the largest lobbying group in the US, the U.S. Chamber of Commerce (USCC) (I know, sounds like it’s a government entity) has spent around $40m in 2022. It mostly represents the interests of a handful of so-called “legacy industries”: industries like tobacco, banking and fossil fuels which have been around for generations and learned how to leverage their earnings into political influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big one is the NRA (National Rifle Association), which has spent approximately $11m during the same period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But unlike the NRA, which supports mostly Republicans, AIPAC has a bipartisan approach. It supports candidates from both Republican and Democratic parties, as long as they align with its pro-Israel stance. In this manner, no matter which party is in power, AIPAC’s agenda remains a priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[January 20, 2025 Update] I must say, I am watching &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eS-JeYb2ED0&amp;amp;t=1235s&quot;&gt;President Trump’s inauguration speech&lt;/a&gt; right now, and the only time that Biden/Kamala/former presidents, not only clap (okay they also clapped when he said he wants to go to Mars, otherwise Trump was just indirectly roasting them), but stand up and clap, is after Trump says this:
“The hostages in the Middle East are coming back home to their families”. Obviously, he’s talking only about the Israeli hostages. This is the only thing they all agree on. Isn’t that a coincidence? Like, Kamala must’ve thought “Oh shoot, better get up and clap or else I’ll be losing free money”. Every time Kamala clapped her hands together, she probably made like $10k.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;christian-zionism&quot;&gt;Christian Zionism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lUQ_0MubbcM&quot;&gt;this video of Noam Chomsky&lt;/a&gt; talking a bit about Christian Zionism. Christian Zionism is the belief that the return of Jews to their historic homeland fulfills biblical prophecy. This belief isn’t shared by all Christians, but it’s particularly strong among Evangelical Christians in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Christians tend to read the Bible literally, so when it says the land of Israel belongs to the Jews, they take it at face value &lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(Note on specific section of the Bible)&lt;/a&gt;. They believe that the Jewish return to Israel a is prerequisite for the Second Coming of Christ. &lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;(Note on Zionism vs. Christian Zionism)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, in the US, there are about 70-80 million Evangelical Christians (its very hard to say, take these numbers with a grain of salt, but in 2012 The Economist estimated that “over one-third of Americans, more than 100 million”, can be considered evangelical), and a significant number of them believe that supporting Israel aligns with biblical prophecy. The point is that there are a lot of them, and a lot of them are also politicians (from names we know, there’s Ted Cruz, Marco Rubio, Ron DeSantis, George W. Bush, Mike Pompeo, Mike Pence. Very popular within the Republican Party as we can see, but I have not done extensive research). &lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;(Note on other types of Christians)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we go back in time, Woodrow Wilson, the US President during WW1, was a devout Christian who read the Bible daily. Harry Truman, the president who officially recognized Israel in 1948, 11 minutes after it was declared, shared similar religious convictions. Truman even &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarsarchive.byu.edu/byusq/vol34/iss1/2/#:~:text=The%20US%20was%20the%20first,as%20recorded%20in%20Ezra%201.&quot;&gt;likened himself to Cyrus&lt;/a&gt;, a Persian king in the Bible who allowed the Jews to return to their homeland after captivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even during Franklin D. Roosevelt’s administration (the president during WW2), Harold Ickes, a senior official, described the return of Jews to Palestine as one of the greatest historical events, rooted in fulfilling biblical prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the British elites in the early 20th century, many were deeply Christian (although not necessarily Evangelicals). Their beliefs were shaped by a mix of Christian tradition and a sense of cultural superiority tied to their empire. They probably thought that they were fulfilling biblical prophecy by helping the Jews return to their “promised land”. This mindset (I don’t know what else was in it for him) influenced Arthur Balfour, the British Foreign Secretary who, in 1917, issued the Balfour Declaration. This was a letter expressing the British government’s support for creating a national home for the Jewish people in Palestine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The letter was addressed to Lord Walter Rothschild, a member of the famous Rothschild family, which was one of the wealthiest families in the world at the time &lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;(Note on the Rothschild family)&lt;/a&gt;. They were bankers with ties to many Jewish causes, and although Walter Rothschild wasn’t a Zionist leader himself, he became the intermediary between British officials and the Zionist movement, led by figures like Chaim Weizmann, David Ben-Gurion, and the father of Zionism, Theodor Herzl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, all this just to give another angle of this deeply-rooted support that the US has towards Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 1967, Egypt, led by President Gamal Abdel Nasser, moved large numbers of troops into the Sinai Peninsula, close to Israel’s border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nasser has also ordered the United Nations Emergency Force (UNEF), which had been stationed in Sinai since the Suez Crisis of 1956 to maintain peace, to withdraw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, Egypt blocked Israeli shipping through the Straits of Tiran, a critical shipping channel for Israel’s trade route to Asia and oil supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this amid public threats made by Nasser and other Arab leaders to destroy Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in response, in June 1967, Israel launched a surprise air assault that decimated Egypt’s air force on the ground. This gave Israel air superiority and set the stage for rapid territorial gains in what became a six-day conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#some-history&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually pretty crazy. King Hussein’s grandfather, King Abdullah I, was assassinated (by a Palestinian in Jerusalem, linked to the Muslim Brotherhood) back when he was the king of Jordan in 1951, and at the time Prince Hussein (later to become the king), was also shot but he survived thanks to a medal on his uniform deflecting the shot. This was the first assassination attempt. The second one attempt happened when he was King, in Jordan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And apparently for many years, King Hussein was on the CIA payroll? You can google if interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#palestinians&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea is rooted in specific passages in the Old Testament, such as Genesis 17:8, where God promises Abraham and his descendants the land of Canaan as an “everlasting possession”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#christian-zionism&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While both movements support the existence of Israel, they do so for different reasons. Jewish Zionism is about the Jewish people, about their survival and their right for self-determination, while Christian Zionism is about fulfilling what some Christians interpret as God’s plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is rooted in Jewish history, culture, and religion, as well as a response to centuries of antisemitism and persecution, especially in Europe. The other is rooted in a specific interpretation of the Bible, particularly the Old Testament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#christian-zionism&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what do other Christians believe? Protestants, Catholics, and Orthodox Christians usually interpret the Bible less literally. They might see these promises as symbolic or tied to ancient history rather than something that applies today. Their focus tends to be on spiritual teachings and broader lessons, not specific prophecies about land or nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#christian-zionism&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rothschild family played a significant role in supporting the establishment of Israel, both through their financial resources and their political influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all started with Mayer Amschel Rothschild (1744–1812), who was born in the ghetto (“Jew Alley”, as it was called) in Frankfurt Germany. He established a banking business there (the Church has historically seen charging interest, i.e. profiting from loaning money, as sinful, so that occupation was dominated by Jews). He assigned each of his five sons to expand and establish the family’s operations in major European cities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amschel Mayer Rothschild (Frankfurt)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salomon Mayer Rothschild (Vienna)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nathan Mayer Rothschild (London)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carl Mayer Rothschild (Naples)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Mayer Rothschild (Paris)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With time, they financed governments, infrastructure projects, and wars across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Mayer Rothschild of the Paris branch had a grandson named Edmond de Rothschild (1845-1934) who was dubbed  “The Father of the Yishuv” (“Yishuv” is the Jewish community in Palestine before Israel was established in 1948. It literally means “settlement”). Why was he called that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Edmond financed early Jewish settlements in Palestine, helping them purchase land and establish agricultural villages (started in the 1880s). He provided funds for irrigation, farming equipment, and infrastructure development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edmond was from the French branch, while Walter (1868–1937) was from the British branch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Economics" /><summary type="html">So I was writing this as a “side note” in the article of “Naked Econ Summary Part 3”, specifically after Chapter 8, but it got way too long, and so I put this in a separate article.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 3 of Reading Naked Economics</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 3 of Reading Naked Economics" /><published>2024-12-19T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2024-12-19T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-3/">&lt;p&gt;This is Part 3 of my summary of “Naked Economics: Undressing the Dismal Science”. It covers more topics, including politics, globalization, trade, and development economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-8-the-power-of-organized-interests&quot;&gt;Chapter 8. The Power of Organized Interests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-9-keeping-score&quot;&gt;Chapter 9. Keeping Score&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-8-the-power-of-organized-interests&quot;&gt;Chapter 8. The Power of Organized Interests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous chapters, the author has mentioned about “creative destruction”, which is a term he uses to describe how technological advancements (the “creative” part), disrupt industries and its workers (the “destruction” part).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine that entire industry, all of its people come up and do what they can to prevent the implementation of the more efficient technology into their field, to avoid losing their jobs. &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(Note 1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what this chapter touches upon: how can a group of people, however small, affect change in the country. In other words, politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-interesting-case-study&quot;&gt;An interesting case study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author starts the chapter by talking about mohair farmers. Mohair is like wool, but it comes from the Angora goat, which looks like a sheep/goat hybrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, during the 1940’s and 50’s, there was a lot of tension in the world, a lot of wars (think WW2 and the Korean war (1950-1953)). Wool was used in uniforms. And half of all the wool used was imported in. So to lower their dependence on foreign fibers, the government created the National Wool Act in 1954, which is a subsidy for wool, and other types of similar fibers such as mohair. This subsidy lasted until 1993.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously you’re wondering, well what’s the problem? The government didn’t want to depend on on foreign imports, so they subsidize a domestic industry in order to “prompt it up”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the military switched to using synthetic fibers in 1960.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So allow me to recap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1940s: Military uses wool in uniforms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1955: Mohair subsidy is created in order to promote domestic mohair production.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1960: Military stops using wool and mohair in uniforms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1993: Wool/mohair subsidy is removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now the big question: Why the hell was the subsidy in place for 33 years after the supposed reason for its creation no longer existed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the early 1990s, about 80% of domestic mohair was produced for export markets (this is what I read online). Meaning the US definitely didn’t need all that mohair anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you may say “Well everything with the government is just slow. It was just a matter of time before they removed this subsidy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That may be true, but then explain why a similar subsidy came back in the 2008 Farm Bill, which included wool and mohair farmers as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are mohair farmers included yet again in this bill? Is there a powerful group of mohair farmers who are influencing congress?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, not at all. These are just regular farmers. In fact, it is precisely because there aren’t many of them that they’re able to secure these benefits. Here’s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine 300 million Americans each paying a few extra cents in taxes. Those pennies are barely noticeable to the average person. However, for a small group of mohair farmers, these subsidies amount to tens of thousands of dollars per farmer. To the farmers, this is life-changing money. To everyone else, it’s too insignificant to raise concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For politicians, this is a golden opportunity. Promise a policy that benefits a small, organized group like mohair farmers, and you’ve just secured their unwavering support. Now, multiply this by thousands of such niche groups: dairy farmers, wool farmers, peanut growers, etc. Each group gets its subsidy, and the politician gains millions of votes without facing much backlash. Why? Because for the average voter, these subsidies are just a rounding error in their tax bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomenon highlights a fundamental quirk in democracy: small, concentrated groups with a lot to gain can wield disproportionate influence over policies. It’s a classic case of dispersed costs and concentrated benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mAsaE7LuiRU&quot;&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt; is such a great summary of this exact situation. Watching this 3-minute clip will reinforce these topics in your head, and basically confirms most of what I wrote here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whatever-gets-the-votes&quot;&gt;Whatever gets the votes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, the author talks about ethanol. (Just keep in mind that this book was published in 2013, so scientific data has probably evolved, however I did briefly look into it, mainly its the same).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethanol is a corn-based gasoline additive thought to be renewable and environmentally friendly. The gas we use in our cars, for example, actually is 10% ethanol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The science backing ethanol is not very strong though. Some studies show it’s less polluting, but others say that it evaporates faster than pure gasoline, contributing to ozone problems. To make ethanol, you have to grow corn, and corn farming has negative effects on the environment (due to land-use changes, due to runoff from fertilizer and pesticides, etc.). Also, there was an idea that using ethanol would decrease the US’s reliance on foreign oil (this happened especially during the 1970s oil crisis). That was also shown to be an dubious theory. If you want to learn more about the science, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F-yDKeya4SU&quot;&gt;watch this video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as was written in the New York Times in 2000 (during the 2000 presidential race), &lt;em&gt;“Regardless of whether ethanol is a great fuel for cars, it certainly works wonders in Iowa campaigns”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill Bradley was a senator from New Jersey who was known for opposing the ethanol subsidy. It seems he had looked into the data and found little backing for its claims. Good on him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 1992, Bill Bradley was running as a Democratic presidential candidate, and he visited Iowa. All of a sudden, he decided that he actually loves ethanol and wants to support the farmers involved in ethanol production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a coincidence. That in the crucial state of Iowa, a swing state (back then), where lots of people are corn-farmers, this candidate had a sudden change of heart on this matter. Definitely not a political strategy to pander to the voters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since, every single mainstream presidential candidate has supported the ethanol subsidy, except for one: John McCain. Notice how McCain was never the president. Obama, on the other hand, did support the ethanol subsidy. (I’m obviously not saying this is why Obama won in Iowa, but it could be one of many reasons).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/naked-econ/iowa-election.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Obama McCain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again, the theory is that a small, well-organized group, has lots of power politically, because the cost of whatever favor they may ask for is spread over a large, unorganized population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teachers-in-the-wrong&quot;&gt;Teachers in the wrong&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love teachers, and think they should get compensated more, however this is not the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every state requires public school teachers to get certain certificates. In Illinois, these requirements have steadily increased over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like a good thing at first: we want potential teachers to be well-trained before teaching our children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that current teachers don’t have to jump through the same hoops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, if we are adding new training requirements with the supposition that this will benefit students, then the fact that current teachers don’t also need to take the additional tests or certifications makes no sense. Think about it: you have a 25-year-old teacher who will be teaching for the next 40 years, while a 22-year-old aspiring teacher must complete more training than the 25-year-old had to just 2-3 years ago. If taking these extra courses or exams is necessary to be a good teacher, then presumably anyone standing at the front of the classroom should have to do them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the best teacher, with 20 years experience, coming from a private school, cannot teach at a public school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was a study done in California, and it showed that a. Good teachers matter, and b. certification has no correlation with how good a teacher is. The authors of this study recommended that states eliminate entry barriers so that talented people can become public school teachers. Most states are doing the opposite by adding more hoops to jump through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that there are many extra hoops, and this was done thanks to the teachers’ union lobby. Why? Because current teachers have to worry less about their job being taken by future teachers entering the workforce. There is less supply of teachers and, as a result, less competition for current teachers. And that’s what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in the state of Illinois, electricians don’t need to be licensed, but barbers and manicurists do. So my house can get burned down from a bad electrical job, but we cannot allow for my barber to be off by 1mm in my haircut. So, clearly, the danger level of a profession is not correlated with licensure. What is correlated with licensure is the political organization of a group. Groups seek to get themselves licensed. (Not saying that electricians are completely unregulated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-not-stop-creative-destruction&quot;&gt;Do not stop creative destruction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a policymaker, you want to make sure you don’t end up focusing your efforts on protecting methods and skills that are in decline. For example, if cigarette smoking has steadily decreased over the last 40 years, it makes sense to address the challenges faced by tobacco farmers whose livelihoods are threatened by this decline. The government should step in to assist them, but it should not aim to keep them in business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, funds collected from legal settlements with the tobacco industry could be used to compensate tobacco farmers and support their transition into other types of farming or entirely new industries. This approach provides meaningful help without trying to artificially sustain an industry that is shrinking for good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is to recognize the importance of letting creative destruction take its course. By holding on to outdated practices simply to preserve the status quo, we risk stifling innovation and progress. Change can be challenging, but it is also essential for long-term growth. &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(Note 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quotes-from-ch8&quot;&gt;Quotes from Ch.8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In countries where farmers make up a small fraction of the population, such as America and Europe, the government provides large subsidies for agriculture. But in countries where the farming population is relatively large, such as China and India, the subsidies go the other way. Farmers are forced to sell their crops at below-market prices so that urban dwellers can get basic food items cheaply. […] What makes these examples logically consistent is that in both cases the large group subsidizes the smaller group.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The cost of [the mohair subsidy] is insignificant in the face of our $14 trillion economy. So is the ethanol subsidy. So is the trade protection for sugar producers, and the tax break for pharmaceutical companies with operations in Puerto RIco, and the price supports for dairy farmers. But in total, these things - and the tens of thousands of others like them - &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; signification. Little inefficiencies begin to disrupt the basic function of a market economy: taking inputs and producing goods and services as efficiently as possible. If the government has to support the price of milk, the real problem is that there are too many dairy farmers. […] Governments should not be in the business of providing incentives for people to do things that would not otherwise make sense.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Both politics and compassion suggest that we ought to offer a hand to those mowed over by competition. If some kind of wrenching change generates progress, then the pie must get bigger. And if the pie gets bigger, then at least some of it ought to be offered to the losers - be it in the form of transition aid, job retraining, or whatever else will help those who have been knocked over to get back on their feet. […] There is a crucial distinction, however, between using the political process to build a safety net for those harmed by creative destruction and using the political process to stop that creative destruction in the first place. Think about the telegraph and the Pony Express. It would have been one thing to help displaced Pony Express workers by retraining them as telegraph operators; it would have been quite another to help them by banning the telegraph. Sometimes the political process does the equivalent of the latter for reasons related to the mohair problem. The economic benefits of competitions are huge but spread over a large group; the costs tend to be smaller but highly concentrated. As a result, the beneficiaries of creative destruction hardly notice; the losers chain themselves to their congressman’s office door seeking protection, as any of us might if our livelihood or community were at risk.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-9-keeping-score&quot;&gt;Chapter 9. Keeping Score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When ChatGPT came out, we quickly saw that some people were opposed to it. Obviously, all technology has its pros and cons, but that’s when I learned about the Luddites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Luddite is someone opposed to new technology or new ways of working. The term is often used in a derogatory way today, but it has its roots in a real historical movement. The Luddites were English textile workers in the early 1800s who protested against industrial machines that threatened their jobs. They sabotaged looms and other machinery, trying to stop the changes that would disrupt their livelihoods. By 1812, machine-breaking was declared a crime punishable by death, and 17 men were executed the following year for their actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to dismiss them as people afraid of progress, but their livelihoods were at stake. When your way of life is under threat, it is hard to see the bigger picture. Over time, though, progress tends to benefit society, even if it forces painful changes along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading this chapter, I will say that being a politician is no simple task. It is easy to say, “Just do the right thing”, but what does that mean sometimes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you stand up to the ethanol lobby and risk losing Iowa, or do you support something you might not believe in because winning means you can do good elsewhere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every decision has trade-offs. Every choice comes with consequences, and there is always someone unhappy with what you do. It is not just about knowing what is right; it is about navigating the messy reality of how to make it happen without losing everything in the process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Books" /><category term="Economics" /><summary type="html">This is Part 3 of my summary of “Naked Economics: Undressing the Dismal Science”. It covers more topics, including politics, globalization, trade, and development economics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Unexpected Exception</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/some-thoughts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Unexpected Exception" /><published>2024-11-19T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2024-11-19T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/some-thoughts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/some-thoughts/">&lt;p&gt;I used to not understand car enthusiasts, wine enthusiasts, sneaker collectors, or art lovers. But now I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not because I now enjoy these things myself, but because I got into something that is, in my opinion, more extreme than the interests listed above. I think I picked up an edge case; I’ve reached a boundary of interests, and so anything within the boundary is understandable now. I didn’t even know this edge case existed. I didn’t know it was a thing. And I certainly didn’t think that it could be a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-most-useless-object-i-own&quot;&gt;The Most Useless Object I Own&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I absolutely abhor materialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know how there are the five love languages? Physical touch, quality time, acts of service, words of affirmation, and receiving gifts. Well, “gifts” ranks so low for me it shouldn’t even be on the list. The thought of accumulating more possessions feels like a burden. I feel like it creates an obligation to keep, display, or use the thing. I don’t want to be cluttered with objects and their underlying obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing: the wristwatch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A perfect example of human irrationality. The time is everywhere around us now: phones, laptops, stoves, car displays. A mechanical timepiece on your wrist makes about as much sense as riding a horse to work (unless you’re one of the few people who actually dive to the bottom of the ocean and require one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it gets better. People spend thousands of dollars on watches, and some wait years on a waitlist for the privilege to spend $50,000 on one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best part? They all keep worse time than a $30 quartz watch from the mall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because we have already established that watches are redundant and irrational, arguing about accuracy does nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing up accuracy here is like criticizing a painting because it doesn’t look as realistic as a photograph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like arguing that a Toyota is more reliable than a Pagani. Sure, it’s true, but it completely misses the point of why people are drawn to expensive cars in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a car guy. To me, the point of a car is to get me from point A to point B. I can do that in a Corolla. I don’t need a Mercedes CLS 63 AMG to do so. But for some people, a car is more than a piece of metal on wheels. It’s a chamber in which they spend hours a day, getting around the city. So they want to make that time special. They want something that brings them joy every time they sit in it (even if that joy might’ve stemmed from clever marketing and social conditioning). They want something unique that makes them recognizable. When friends see their car in a parking lot, they know that person has arrived. The car becomes an extension of who they are. Even though you’re spending more on premium fuel and getting worse mileage, the emotional aspect weighs more than the extra money spent on fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a watch is even more useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least with an expensive car, you get tangible improvements: you can feel the acceleration push you back in your seat, the premium leather against your skin, the warmth of the heated steering wheel on cold mornings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With watches? Nothing like that. It’s just some gears and springs placed into a case, and they all do exactly the same thing: tell time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But again, the premise here is wrong because telling time isn’t even the point anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you walk through a local artisan market, you don’t expect to get the best deal on a handmade leather wallet. You don’t expect it to compete in price with mass-produced wallets from Chinese factories. You understand you’re paying more for something crafted by hand with materials bought at retail price, along with years of expertise and hours of labor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We respect skilled artisans, whether they’ve dedicated their lives to their craft or create simply for the love of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not about efficiency anymore. One factory worker with access to specialized machinery will produce more output than 50 artisans in the same time frame. This principle applies to almost any item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a watchmaker who spends a year crafting a single watch. When someone buys it for over $100k, people criticize the purchase. But that price reflects the time spent making it, the years of learning the craft, and the living costs of being based in expensive countries like Switzerland or Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But again, at least a handmade leather wallet is useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, to that I say: buying a watch is a romantic idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world full of disposable electronics and planned obsolescence, mechanical watches, to me at least, stand out. Each one contains countless moving parts, powered by nothing but gears and springs. Hand-assembled at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an art form, using technology to create something unnecessary. And that’s okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s technology created not to push boundaries in a practical sense, but purely to exist as art. Just like a painting doesn’t need to revolutionize visual representation to be worthwhile, a watch doesn’t need to improve timekeeping to justify its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, watchmaking still pushes boundaries, but only for the sake of beauty, tradition, or technical challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/Richard-Mille-RM-UP-01-Ferrari-Thinnest-Mechanical-Watch-1.75mm-Record-8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;RM watch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some try to make the thinnest watch ever, like the Richard Mille RM UP-01, which is just 1.75 millimeters thick. Others build watches that show the phase of the moon, track multiple time zones at once, or automatically adjust for the length of each month, even in leap years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this is necessary. That is what makes it interesting. It is not about telling time. It exists because someone wanted to, not because anyone needed it (although some features are actually useful, such as tracking multiple time zones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-choose-watches-over-tattoos&quot;&gt;Why I Choose Watches Over Tattoos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how I see watch collecting: some people choose to engrave a tattoo onto their skin, marking an experience they want to remember. Their body becomes a book, telling their life story. When they’re older, they can look at their body and see glimpses of their life events. To me, this is the most compelling argument for tattoos, but I would never do it myself, as I’m not confident that I will always want a permanent reminder of a temporary feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a watch you wear daily though, you get a similar personal connection without the permanence. While you might not afford as many watches as you can tattoos, this just means the milestones they represent will be fewer but more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The milestones worth celebrating vary for everyone, but let’s keep perspective. Buying watches remains fundamentally consumerist, and without restraint it becomes pure materialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even if all this sounds too philosophical, at least a watch can upgrade your look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a pretty good worst-case scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I could continue on this point, saying how a nice watch from “a real watch brand” sends a message to the world, whether you like it or not. Walk into some business meeting with thousands of dollars wrapped around your wrist, and if the other person recognizes it, you’re starting ahead without saying a word. When people see signs of financial success, they’re more likely to listen. Sure, you could talk your way to that same credibility, but an expensive watch does that preliminary “get-to-know-you talk” partially for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But obviously, you shouldn’t buy a watch just for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do it because you personally want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I do is I casually browse online, keep a mental list of any watch within my budget that I like, and over months see which one I consistently gravitate towards. After that much time, I’m usually quite certain about my choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sharing this because the most important reasons should be internal, not external validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-note-on-ultra-luxury&quot;&gt;A Note On Ultra-Luxury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luxury has always been about distinguishing the ruling class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the days, the upper class would separate themselves by having specific rules about how to eat (which fork to use for which course, how to hold a teacup), how to walk (proper posture, the right way to bow), and how to speak (proper pronunciation, acceptable conversation topics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, many “luxury” items are more accessible to regular people. Anyone can walk into a Louis Vuitton store and buy a bag if they save up enough money. So luxury brands needed to find a new way to make their highest tier items feel exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Porsche’s limited edition cars. You can’t just buy a GT3 RS. You have to convince them to let you buy it. You start by buying a few other models, one for your wife, one for your kid, one for yourself. A few years later, you trade in a car for a newer model. Then, you tell them you’d be interested in the limited edition model. And then maybe, just maybe, if you’re lucky and they think you’d be a good ambassador to the brand, they give you the honor to spend hundreds of thousands of dollars (and 100k over MSRP due to demand) on the limited edition car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same goes for certain watches and handbags. You can’t simply walk into a store and buy a Rolex Daytona or an Hermès Birkin, no matter how much money you have. You need a purchase history. You need to be deemed worthy. When money becomes more common, the truly wealthy need new ways to stay exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rich people today can buy almost anything they want. Everything is accessible to them. So when someone finally tells them &lt;em&gt;“no, you can’t have this”&lt;/em&gt;, it creates an interesting dynamic. Finally, a challenge. Finally, something they can’t just throw money at. They have to prove themselves worthy again, like back when they were nobodies. They have to earn their spot, build relationships, show interest and loyalty to the brand. Money becomes just the entry fee to this game of acquiring a status object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-swiss-pride-met-japanese-precision&quot;&gt;When Swiss Pride Met Japanese Precision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a certain snobbery in the watch world about Swiss watches. Some people believe that only Swiss watches can be considered “proper” watches, dismissing everything else as inferior. This bias makes the following story particularly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Precise timekeeping has always been crucial for navigation, especially at sea where timing errors can compound into dangerous miscalculations. This pursuit of accuracy led to chronometer competitions at astronomical observatories. By the 1960s, the most prestigious of these was held at the Neuchâtel Observatory, in Neuchâtel, Switzerland. Swiss manufacturers dominated these competitions, with companies like Omega, Patek Philippe, and Zenith regularly achieving top results. The goal with these competitions was to create the most accurate mechanical movement possible, without regard for cost or practicality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Swiss dominance continued unchallenged until Seiko, a Japanese company, decided to enter the race in 1964. Their first attempt resulted in their best movement placing 144th. After discovering their movements had gotten magnetized during transport, they began shipping them in anti-magnetic cases and planned routes farther from the Earth’s magnetic north pole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Year after year, Seiko’s rankings improved. From 114th place in 1965, they reached 9th in 1966. By 1967, they achieved places 4th through 13th. Then came to the 1968 competition. The swiss simply canceled it midway through when it looked like Seiko might win (obviously this is not an official story), claiming they needed to “reevaluate the rules”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While still in Switzerland with their competition-ready movements, Seiko entered the Geneva Observatory competition. There, they secured all positions from 4th to 10th place. The crazy part is that the Swiss took the top three spots using battery-powered movements, which are inherently more precise than mechanical ones. In other words, among purely mechanical watches, Seiko had actually achieved positions 1 through 7. They won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marked the end of the observatory chronometer competitions. 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they revived the chronometer competition in 2009, they included an interesting requirement: All parts and watches entered must be manufactured in Europe. This basically barred any Asian manufacturers from participating, and, in my opinion, strips this competition of any credibility it might have once had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Swiss used battery-powered movements to protect their dominance in 1968, something ironic was about to happen. Just a year later, in 1969, Seiko released the Astron, the world’s first fully-integrated &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(Note 1)&lt;/a&gt; quartz watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This led to what Swiss watchmakers would later call the “quartz crisis”. As electronic watches became cheaper, the mechanical watch industry in Switzerland nearly collapsed. In just a decade, two thirds of the jobs in the Swiss watchmaking industry vanished. Once a bunch of the dying companies were bought out (hence why there are like three companies that own most of the Swiss brands today), they redefined what watches represent to consumers by appealing to the artistry and the craft rather than the precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my favorite story about watches. And makes me respect Seiko so much. Because they don’t even use all this in their marketing. They don’t put the Swiss down for all this. You know the story, now you can go &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seikowatches.com/us-en/special/heritage/&quot;&gt;read what they put on their website, under the 1967 date&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So next time you see a watch and it’s not from Switzerland, remember there’s more to watchmaking than Swiss marketing would have you believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term “fully integrated quartz” in watchmaking means all the components (the quartz crystal oscillator, the integrated circuit, the stepping motor, and the display) were miniaturized and engineered to work together in a single wristwatch case. Earlier attempts at electronic watches used batteries or some electronic components (like the ones used to “win” the 1968 Geneva competition), but weren’t able to integrate all these parts into a practical wristwatch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seiko Astron was revolutionary because it was the first to successfully combine all these elements into a complete, wearable quartz watch. Prior electronic or battery powered watches still relied on mechanical parts for some of their functions, while the Astron represented a completely new way of keeping time using quartz crystal technology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html">I used to not understand car enthusiasts, wine enthusiasts, sneaker collectors, or art lovers. But now I do.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 2 of Reading Naked Economics</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 2 of Reading Naked Economics" /><published>2024-11-10T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2024-11-10T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-2/">&lt;p&gt;This is Part 2 of my summary of “Naked Economics: Undressing the Dismal Science”. It only covers Chapter 7: Financial Markets, starting with a summary of the chapter, and then I dive into topics of interest to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-7-financial-markets&quot;&gt;Chapter 7: Financial Markets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial products and instruments can get complicated. We have stocks and bonds, but we also have options, futures, commodities, and credit default swaps. Actually, things got so complicated and opaque that even the professionals didn’t fully understand the products they were buying and selling, which is exactly how we ended up with 2008. No matter the complexity in finance, no matter all the jargon and frantic activity that happens on Wall Street, everything that happens in a financial market always boils down to these four fundamental needs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Raising capital:&lt;/strong&gt; Individuals (through a credit card, or a bank loan), companies (through debt financing by issuing bonds or through equity financing by selling stocks), and governments (through treasury bonds or municipal bonds) need capital to do things today that they could not otherwise afford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Storing, protecting, and making profitable use of excess capital:&lt;/strong&gt;  If you hold cash, it will get eaten away by inflation. And the world is full of prospective borrowers, all of whom are willing to pay for the privilege of accessing your cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is a reason that “interest” in math formulas are not denoted with an “&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;”, but with an “&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;”: the “rental rate” on capital. Individuals/companies are renting out their cash to others who can make more productive use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Insuring Against Risk:&lt;/strong&gt; Risk aversion is one of humans’ most fundamental characteristics &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(Note 1)&lt;/a&gt;. We hate to lose. So we don’t mind paying a bit every month to feel safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all familiar with health, life and car insurance. They work by charging everyone a bit more than they expect to pay out, averaged over everyone. So they make a profit, those who need the money will get it, and those who don’t need it at least got a peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Anything can be insured. For example, a French oil tanker was rammed by a suicide bomber in 2002 off the coast of Yemen, and the insurance company ended up paying $70M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Speculation:&lt;/strong&gt; Financial products can also be used to bet on short-term price movements. You can bet that the price of Microsoft stock in two hours will be higher than it is right now. While on average, over a long period, prices do go up, in the short-term, things are harder to predict. That’s what sports and financial products have in common: they facilitate gambling, even if that is not their primary purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s now dive deeper into specific topics in finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;starbucks-and-hedging&quot;&gt;Starbucks and Hedging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the price of coffee beans over the past 50+ years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/naked-econ/coffee-price.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Price of coffee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Historical graph of coffee beans price as found on https://tradingeconomics.com/commodity/coffee.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s anything but stable. Coffee prices &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(Note 2)&lt;/a&gt; bounce all over the place, thanks to unpredictable factors like weather &lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(Note 3)&lt;/a&gt;, politics, and crop diseases in coffee-growing regions. Now, the question is, &lt;strong&gt;why doesn’t the price of your Pumpkin Spice Latte follow this graph?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in Starbucks’ best interest to avoid being hit by unpredictable jumps in global coffee prices. So, Starbucks hedges against price swings by using futures contracts. A futures contract is simply an agreement to buy a set amount of coffee beans at a specific price, months or even years in advance. By locking in prices this way, Starbucks protects itself from short-term volatility: if coffee prices soar, they still pay the lower, agreed-upon price. If prices drop, well, they miss out on a deal. And that’s okay, because the goal for Starbucks is to keep prices predictable so that a Pumpkin Spice Latte will cost around the same for longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a similar story on the coffee producer’s side. By using futures contracts, coffee growers can lock in a price for their beans even before harvest, giving them a stable income they can rely on. While they could wait and hope for higher prices, they face risks like fluctuating demand and potential increases in global coffee supply, both of which could push prices down unexpectedly. These growers are willing to trade some potential gains for the security of a reliable income. This is insurance, just like health or car insurance, providing a safety net against the ups and downs of the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, futures contracts fall into the “3. Insuring Against Risk” category, right? Everyone is willing to pay a little price in order to ensure stability. Airlines use futures contracts to lock in a predictable price for jet fuel. Fast-food restaurants use them for ground beef, pork, and even cheddar cheese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;catastrophe-bonds-a-hedge-against-nature&quot;&gt;Catastrophe Bonds: A Hedge Against Nature&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catastrophe bonds, or “cat bonds,” allow insurance companies to hedge against the financial risks of natural disasters. A bond is essentially a loan from investors to the company; in exchange, investors earn interest and eventually get their principal back. With catastrophe bonds, if a disaster strikes, the insurance company keeps the bond money to cover claims, and investors may lose some or all of their principal. But if no disaster occurs, the investors get their principal back plus interest, making it a high-risk, high-reward investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1990s, the United Services Automobile Association (USAA) issued over $1.5 billion in cat bonds tied to the hurricane season on the East Coast. The terms were straightforward: if there was little or no hurricane damage during the season, investors would get their principal back plus a high annual interest rate of around 12%. If damages exceeded $1.5 billion, they’d lose their principal entirely, while moderate damage between $1 billion and $1.5 billion meant a partial loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary investors in these securities are hedge funds, pension funds, and other institutional investors. The main attraction for them is the high interest rate, often much higher than regular bonds. Plus, because cat bonds are tied to specific natural events rather than the ups and downs of the economy, they offer a steady return even when financial markets aren’t doing well, giving investors a useful buffer when other investments are struggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cancellation-bonds-a-hedge-against-terrorism&quot;&gt;Cancellation Bonds: A Hedge Against Terrorism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, organizations face unique risks that go beyond natural disasters, like the risk of a major event being canceled due to terrorism. For the 2006 World Cup in Germany, the World Football Federation (FIFA) decided to protect itself against the possibility of a catastrophic event leading to the tournament’s cancellation. To do this, FIFA issued $260 million in “cancellation bonds”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bonds worked similarly to catastrophe bonds. Investors would receive interest payments, but if a terrorist attack forced the World Cup to be canceled, FIFA would keep the principal to cover its financial losses. If the event went on as planned without incident, investors would get their money back along with interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The beauty of these products lies in the way they spread risk. The party selling the bonds avoids ruin by sharing the costs of a natural disaster or a terrorist attack with a broad group of investors, each of whom has a diversified portfolio and will therefore take a relatively small hit even if something truly awful happens.”&lt;/em&gt; - Charles Wheelan, Ch.7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;credit-default-swaps-a-hedge-against-default-risk&quot;&gt;Credit Default Swaps: A Hedge Against Default Risk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So imagine we have a borrower and a lender. The lender wants to protect themselves in case the borrower doesn’t pay back the loan. To do this, they buy a credit default swap (CDS) from a third party, known as the CDS seller. The lender pays the CDS seller a regular fee, and in exchange, the CDS seller promises to pay the lender the loan amount if the borrower defaults. This way, the CDS shifts the risk of the borrower not paying from the lender to the CDS seller, giving the lender peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a concrete example: your partner insists that you lend $25,000 to your brother-in-law, but you’re not confident he’ll pay it back. You’re worried that the money might be lost. To protect yourself, you approach a third person who has more faith in your brother-in-law’s ability to repay. You agree to pay this person a small fee, and in return, they promise to cover the $25,000 if your brother-in-law doesn’t pay you back. In this setup, you’re using the third party as a kind of insurance, ensuring you’re protected even if things go wrong with the loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;strong&gt;“Credit Default Swap”&lt;/strong&gt; breaks down like this: &lt;strong&gt;“Credit”&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the loan or debt that’s being insured, &lt;strong&gt;“Default”&lt;/strong&gt; points to the risk that the borrower might not fulfill their payment obligations, and &lt;strong&gt;“Swap”&lt;/strong&gt; describes the agreement between two parties to exchange the risk of default. In short, a Credit Default Swap is a contract that transfers the risk (swap) of a borrower’s failure to repay (default) on a debt obligation (credit) from one party to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-really-owns-your-mortgage&quot;&gt;Who Really Owns Your Mortgage?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine this: I recently bought a home in the US with a mortgage. I make my monthly payments to Wells Fargo. In my mind, Wells Fargo gave me the money to purchase the home, and now I am paying them back the principal amount plus some interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is actually not what happens. Here’s the real story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wells Fargo did initially lend me the money, but they quickly sold my mortgage to someone else (like Fannie Mae or Freddie Mac &lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;(Note 4)&lt;/a&gt;). Both of these are “government-sponsored enterprises” that buy mortgages from banks, providing liquidity so banks can keep issuing new mortgages to homebuyers. They together own or &lt;strong&gt;guarantee&lt;/strong&gt; about half of all mortgages in the US.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wells Fargo now just “services” my loan, meaning:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;They collect my payments&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Handle my paperwork&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deal with any questions I have&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take a small fee for this service&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pass the rest of my payment to the actual owner&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The funny part is that Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac don’t usually keep these mortgages either. They package thousands of mortgages together and create Mortgage Backed Securities (MBS). These MBS are then sold to investors like pension funds, insurance companies, and investment firms. Fannie and Freddie &lt;strong&gt;guarantee&lt;/strong&gt; these MBS by promising investors they’ll get paid even if homeowners default.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The remaining mortgages in the US follow a different path. Some stay with the banks that issued them. Others are packaged into private label MBS by Wall Street firms, similar to Fannie and Freddie’s process but without any government guarantee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, my monthly payment to Wells Fargo actually takes quite a journey. They keep a small servicing fee, but most of my payment goes into a pool with payments from many other homeowners. Investors who bought shares of the MBS receive payments from this entire pool. These investors could be a pension fund in California, an insurance company in Europe, or any number of other institutional investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cds-in-the-real-world&quot;&gt;CDS in The Real World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to Credit Default Swaps (CDS) really quickly. I will assume you remember the brother-in-law analogy I gave. Now let’s use real-world players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we have a pension fund PF1. This pension fund has to invest the money that US citizens contribute through their paychecks. The investments aim to grow this money to pay future retirees. And because peoples’ future depends on this, PF1 must ensure that its investments are very safe. PF1, for example, can only buy securities &lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;(Note 5)&lt;/a&gt; that are rated A or higher. Again, this is an example. So PF1 typically buys government bonds and corporate bonds &lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;(Note 6)&lt;/a&gt; rated A, AA, or AAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bond example: Let’s say PF1 buys a $100 million bond from Company C1. This is essentially PF1 lending $100 million to C1. In return, C1 promises two things: first, they will pay PF1 3.5% interest ($3.5 million) every year for 10 years, and second, they will return the original $100 million at the end of the 10 years. This way, PF1 knows exactly how much money they’ll receive and when they’ll receive it: $3.5 million each year, plus their $100 million back in year 10. That is how a bond works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say there’s a corporate bond rated BBB. While this is still “investment grade” (meaning it’s considered low-risk), it’s below PF1’s required A-rating threshold. However, if insurance giant AIG (which had a stellar AAA rating at the time) sells PF1 a CDS on these BBB-rated bonds, something interesting happens. With AIG’s guarantee through the CDS, PF1 can now effectively treat this investment as AAA-rated. After all, either the company pays its debts, or AAA-rated AIG will pay PF1 instead. So for all intents and purposes, with AIG’s guarantee, that BBB-rated bond becomes as safe as an AAA-rated bond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Continuing from the corporate bond example, let’s see what happens when AIG gets involved with a credit default swap. PF1 is earning 3.5% ($3.5 million) per year on their $100 million BBB-rated bond. Now, they pay AIG a 1% annual fee ($1 million) for the CDS contract. So PF1’s net return is now 2.5% ($2.5 million) per year, but with AAA-rated protection from AIG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is happening not only with corporate bonds, but also mortgages. Remember those mortgage-backed securities (MBS) I mentioned? The same principle applies there. When MBS were rated below what pension funds could buy, they would purchase CDS from AAA-rated companies like AIG to make these investments be safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-can-possibly-go-wrong&quot;&gt;What Can Possibly Go Wrong?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where we may get into a bit of a sticky situation. AIG wasn’t just selling these CDS contracts to PF1. They were selling similar protections to many other pension funds (PF2, PF3, and so on), as well as banks and other institutions worldwide. All in all, they had written CDS contracts on about $441 billion worth of securities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s put this in perspective: AIG was collecting roughly $500 million in annual fees while taking on $441 billion in potential obligations. And the thing is that they only had about $60 billion in total capital to cover potential losses. They were essentially writing insurance policies far beyond their ability to pay if things went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what are the chances that things go wrong, right? What are the chances that suddenly, a bunch of MBS turn bad? For that to happen, a bunch of homeowners would have to default on their mortgage. But even if that happens, the home acts as a collateral in case of a default, and since home prices always rise, it can always be sold for a profit,  right? No downside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this seemingly foolproof logic created dangerous incentives throughout the system. Banks started giving mortgages to just about anyone, even those with poor credit scores, no proof of income, or no down payment. Why? Because they weren’t planning to keep these risky mortgages on their books. They would quickly bundle them into mortgage-backed securities and sell them to investors. Plus, with house prices consistently rising, banks figured that even if borrowers defaulted, they could always seize and sell the house for a profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These risky loans were called subprime mortgages. Many were variable interest loans that started low but could increase significantly after a few years. When interest rates began rising in 2006, monthly payments shot up, and many homeowners couldn’t keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rating agencies (Moody’s, Standard &amp;amp; Poor’s, and Fitch) claimed these mortgage bundles deserved AAA ratings because combining mortgages from different regions created “diversification.” The theory was that while some homeowners might default, the chances of widespread defaults across the entire country were minimal. But there was a fundamental problem with the rating system: these agencies were paid by the very banks whose securities they were rating. If one agency gave a low rating, banks would simply take their business to a competitor. This created a situation where rating agencies had an incentive to give higher ratings to keep their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house of cards finally collapsed when housing prices started falling nationwide in 2007. Suddenly, homes were worth less than their mortgages, and millions of homeowners with unaffordable payments simply walked away. The “safe” collateral that was supposed to protect against losses became nearly worthless. This triggered a cascade of defaults on mortgage-backed securities, and AIG had to pay up on many of their CDS contracts at once. With only $60 billion in capital to cover $441 billion in guarantees, AIG was quickly overwhelmed, forcing the government to step in with a $185 billion bailout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a classic experiment on risk aversion, participants choose between a guaranteed $50 and a coin flip where they could win $100 or get nothing. Despite both options offering the same average outcome, most people pick the guaranteed $50, showing a preference for certainty over risk. This tendency, called risk aversion, is rooted in loss aversion, the idea that people feel losses more intensely than gains, a concept from prospect theory by psychologists Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky. This experiment shows how people often favor the comfort of a sure outcome over the chance of a larger reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/naked-econ/Prospect-Theory.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prospect Theory&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Prospect theory graph showing that losses hit harder than gains, explaining why people tend to avoid risk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-7-financial-markets&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coffee beans are a commodity. Commodities are essential building blocks in the global economy, as they are raw materials used to produce goods and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A commodity is a basic good or raw material that can be bought, sold, or traded. Commodities are typically standardized and interchangeable, meaning one unit of the commodity is essentially the same as another. They’re categorized mainly into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hard Commodities: Natural resources mined or extracted, like gold, oil, and copper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soft Commodities: Agricultural products or livestock, like soybeans, corn, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ca.investing.com/commodities/lean-hogs&quot;&gt;pigs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ca.investing.com/commodities/live-cattle&quot;&gt;cows&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#starbucks-and-hedging&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coffee comes in two main types: Arabica (which most people, and Starbucks, mainly get) and Robusta. Coffee plants thrive in tropical and subtropical climates, and Arabica (the more popular of the two) grows best at higher altitudes. So, the ideal spot for growing coffee? High-altitude regions around the equator. Only a handful of countries meet these conditions: Brazil (which produces around 40% of the world’s coffee), Vietnam (17%), Colombia (8%), Indonesia (7%), and Honduras (5%). Other big producers are Ethiopia, India, Uganda, Mexico, and Peru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such a limited number of coffee-growing regions, any disruption to their agriculture has a big impact on coffee prices worldwide. Take Brazil, for example. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/1975/08/04/archives/frost-in-brazil-sending-coffee-prices-up-frost-in-brazil-raises.html&quot;&gt;July of 1975&lt;/a&gt;, snow hit Brazil for the first time in decades, wiping out nearly half of its coffee trees and sending prices soaring. A similar event happened in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1994-07-12-fi-14722-story.html&quot;&gt;July of 1994&lt;/a&gt;, causing another spike. But it’s not just frost that’s a threat; droughts and irregular rainfall can mess with coffee yields, leading to shortages and price jumps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/naked-econ/brazil-coffee.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Brazil Coffee Weather Impact&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Graph showing historical coffee price spikes due to frost and drought events in Brazil.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#starbucks-and-hedging&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Federal National Mortgage Association (FNMA) is abbreviated to Fannie Mae, and the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation (FHLMC) is nicknamed Freddie Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#who-really-owns-your-mortgage&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A security is a fancy word for any investment product that can be bought and sold, like stocks or bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cds-in-the-real-world&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pension funds typically focus more on bonds than stocks for a fundamental reason: their predictability. Bonds provide regular, fixed interest payments and return the principal at maturity (if there’s no default). While stocks might offer higher potential returns, they’re also more volatile. Since pension funds need to ensure they can make regular payments to retirees well into the future, they prefer the steady, reliable nature of bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cds-in-the-real-world&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Books" /><category term="Economics" /><summary type="html">This is Part 2 of my summary of “Naked Economics: Undressing the Dismal Science”. It only covers Chapter 7: Financial Markets, starting with a summary of the chapter, and then I dive into topics of interest to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 1 of Reading Naked Economics</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 1 of Reading Naked Economics" /><published>2024-10-30T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2024-10-30T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/naked-econ-1/">&lt;p&gt;This is Part 1 of my detailed summary of “Naked Economics: Undressing the Dismal Science”. It covers foundational topics in economics, focusing on markets, incentives, government intervention, information, and human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading this book a second time because I really enjoyed it the first time around. So, I decided to create this detailed summary as a quick refresher for whenever I want to revisit the key points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-1-the-power-of-markets&quot;&gt;Chapter 1. The Power of Markets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-2-incentives-matter&quot;&gt;Chapter 2. Incentives Matter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-3-government-and-the-economy&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: Government and the Economy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-4-government-and-the-economy-2&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: Government and the Economy 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-5-the-economics-of-information&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: The Economics of Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-6-productivity-and-human-capital&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: Productivity and Human Capital&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-the-power-of-markets&quot;&gt;Chapter 1. The Power of Markets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decentralized-order&quot;&gt;Decentralized Order&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s incredible how markets function: the sum of a bunch of self-interested (i.e. selfish) parties forms a fully functioning society. There is nothing wrong with being selfish &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(Note 1)&lt;/a&gt;, as it is selfishness that has led us to civilization. People act to make themselves better off (in theory), and while doing so, they end up making other people better off as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chapter is based on this rhetorical question: Who feeds Paris? Somehow, the stores and restaurants in Paris get the exact amount of food and ingredients that they need in order to feed its citizens (ignoring all the food waste for a moment). The fish you were served at the local restaurant was caught in the Pacific Ocean by a company called Tokyo Seafood Inc. It was then sold to Global Fish Distributors, who transported it by air to Paris. Upon arrival, the fish was delivered to a local wholesaler, from whom the restaurant purchased it and prepared it for your meal. This seamless supply chain ensures Paris is always well-fed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process works because of the (decentralized) market system, where each person, from fishermen to wholesalers, acts in their own best interest but ends up helping everyone. Fishermen sell their catch for the best price (not too high, not too low), distributors and transporters handle logistics to make a profit, and wholesalers manage stock to meet demand. Prices act as signals, indicating scarcity or abundance, and guiding decisions on where resources are needed most. No central planner trying to micromanage and orchestrate the entire dance. Just decentralized and individualized decision-making, driven by incentives and coordinated by prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as we all know, humans aren’t perfect. Some of us lack the self-discipline to do things that we know will make us better off in the long run. So it is not unreasonable for society to help individuals do things which they otherwise would not or could not do. This is where the government and public policy come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quotes-from-ch1&quot;&gt;Quotes from Ch.1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I will argue that a market economy is to economics what democracy is to government: a decent, if flawed, choice among many bad alternatives. Markets are consistent with our views of individual liberty. We may disagree over whether or not the government should compel us to wear motorcycle helmets, but most of us agree that the state should not tell us where to live, what to do for a living, or how to spend our money. True, there is no way to rationalize spending money on a birthday cake for my dog when the same money could have vaccinated several African children. But any system that forces me to spend money on vaccines instead of doggy birthday cakes can only be held together by oppression. The communist governments of the twentieth century controlled their economies by controlling their citizens’ lives. They often wrecked both in the process. During the twentieth century, communist governments killed some 100 million of their own people in peacetime, either by repression or by famine.” &lt;a href=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(Note 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“[We] can and should use the government to modify market in all kinds of ways. The economics battle of the twentieth century was between capitalism and communism. Capitalism won. […] The economic battles of the twenty-first century will be over how unfettered our markets should be.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-incentives-matter&quot;&gt;Chapter 2. Incentives Matter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;science-of-unintended-consequences&quot;&gt;Science of Unintended Consequences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite chapters for sure. So eye-opening on the unintended consequences of setting up a policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the well-meaning idea to require car seats for infants and small children on planes, even though you can currently fly with a “lap child” without buying an extra seat. During the Clinton administration, the FAA pushed for this, arguing that children should have the same protection as adults in case of an accident. It seems logical (I guess?): car seats could save lives in a “rough landing” situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the problem: buying an extra plane seat for the car seat makes flying much more expensive (you are essentially forced to buy an extra plane seat for your little one), so some families might choose to drive to their destination instead. The catch? Driving, even with a car seat, is far more dangerous than flying. So, ironically, this rule could lead to more injuries and deaths, not fewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example: Mexico City, one of the most polluted cities in the world, tried to cut down on pollution in 1989 by requiring cars to stay off the streets one day a week, based on their license plate numbers. The logic was simple: fewer cars, less pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here’s the problem: people who didn’t want the inconvenience just bought extra cars or kept their old ones when buying new ones. The result? More old, dirty cars on the road, making the air quality even worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These examples highlight a key lesson: policies that seem beneficial on the surface can sometimes have hidden costs that outweigh their intended benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say good policy doesn’t exist. London addressed traffic congestion by charging an $8 USD fee for driving in central city areas during rush hour, starting in 2003. Over time, they raised the fee and expanded the coverage area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This policy leverages a basic market principle: raising prices reduces demand. The result? Fewer cars on the road, reduced traffic, increased use of public transit, and faster-moving buses due to less congestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;misaligned-incentives-in-the-corporate-world&quot;&gt;Misaligned Incentives in the Corporate World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private sector has its troubles as well, both at the lowest and highest levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the low end, take a cashier working at Burger King. The cashier might have incentives that don’t align with the company’s best interests. It’s in the cashier’s interest to steal money, perhaps by selling you a meal without recording the transaction and pocketing the cash. Burger King could spend significant resources monitoring its employees for theft, or it could offer an incentive for customers to do the job by putting up a sign that reads “Your meal is free if you don’t get a receipt. Please see a manager”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the higher end of corporate America, consider CEOs. If I own stock in a company, how can I be sure the CEO is acting in my best interest? For instance, two-thirds of corporate mergers don’t add value to the firms involved, and some even harm shareholders. So why do CEOs pursue these often questionable deals? Because it benefits them; bigger companies mean more prestige, higher salaries, and larger perks like private jets. To align their incentives with shareholder interests, companies often pay CEOs in stock options: if the company’s stock does well, they do well too. But this isn’t a perfect solution, as it can drive CEOs to seek short-term gains at the expense of long-term stability. Studies show that firms with large options grants are more prone to accounting fraud and debt defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let’s come back to earth and look at an example of misaligned incentives in our lives: real estate agents. Both from the buy and the sell side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the buy side, you’re looking for a house and want to negotiate the price down. But your agent, who earns a percentage of the purchase price, benefits from a higher price and a quicker sale. Your interests are completely opposite. &lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(Note 3)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the sell side, it seems like your incentives are aligned with your agent’s: both of you want to sell for as much as possible. But consider this: if you’re selling a $300’000 house, your agent could list it at $280’000 and sell it quickly, or list it at $320’000 and wait for a higher offer. The extra $40’000 means a lot to you, but to your agent, it’s only an additional $1’200 after weeks of extra work, extra showings, extra open houses. If I were the agent, I’d sell it quick and move on to the next deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-all-taxes-are-created-equal&quot;&gt;Not All Taxes Are Created Equal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic of incentives also touches the world of taxes. You can’t just say “tax the rich” and expect them to sit still. The rich aren’t static; they adapt. They change their behavior to avoid as much taxation as possible. Take Bjorn Borg, for example. He became wealthy playing tennis, and the Swedish government taxed him heavily. Borg simply moved to Monaco, and Sweden ended up collecting nothing from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the government imposes a heavy tax on red sports cars, most people will just stop buying red cars. The result? The government collects no revenue, and car enthusiasts miss out on driving their favorite red sports cars. This phenomenon, where taxes make individuals worse off without benefiting anyone else, is known as “deadweight loss”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, it’s better to have a broad tax. It’s harder to evade since fewer activities are exempt, and the tax rate can be lower because it’s spread across more people. This way, there’s less incentive to dodge it. But even with broad taxes, you have to be careful: if everyone pays the same tax, it hits the poor harder because it takes up a larger portion of their income. This kind of tax is called a regressive tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quotes-from-ch2&quot;&gt;Quotes from Ch.2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definition to understand the quotes:&lt;/strong&gt; Creative destruction is a term that describes the process in which new innovations and technologies replace outdated ones, leading to economic progress but also causing disruption as older industries and jobs become obsolete. It’s a core feature of market economies, driving growth and improving efficiency, even though it can be disruptive in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Capitalism can be a brutal, cruel process. We look back and speak admiringly of technological breakthroughs like the steam engine, the spinning wheel, and the telephone. But those advances made it a bad time to be, respectively, a blacksmith, a seamstress, or a telegraph operator. Creative destruction is not just something that might happen in a market economy. It is something that must happen. At the beginning of the twentieth century, half of all Americans worked in farming or ranching. Now that figure is about one in a hundred and still falling. […] Note that two important things have not happened: (1) We have not starved to death; and (2) we do not have a 49 percent unemployment rate. Instead, American farmers have become so productive that we need far fewer of them to feed ourselves. The individuals who would have been farming ninety years ago are now fixing our cars, designing computer games, playing professional football, etc. Just imagine our collective loss of utility if Steve Jobs, Steven Spielberg, and Oprah Winfrey were corn farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creative destruction is a tremendous positive force in the long run. THe bad news is that people don’t pay their bills in the long run.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“During the Industrial Revolution, weavers in rural England demonstrated, petitioned Parliament, and even burned down textile mills in an effort to fend off mechanization. Would we be better off now if they had succeeded and we still made all of our clothes by hand?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-government-and-the-economy&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: Government and the Economy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;negative-externalities&quot;&gt;Negative Externalities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the free market is that if you let it roam free, it will destroy the planet. Why? &lt;strong&gt;Negative externalities: those cases in which individuals or companies engage in private actions that have harmful consequences for society at large.&lt;/strong&gt; The market, if left alone, actually encourages individuals and firms to cut corners in ways that make themselves better off, but make society as a whole worse off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this scenario: A large agricultural company produces a pesticide that seeps into local water supplies, poisoning families. There’s no market solution here; &lt;strong&gt;the market itself is the problem&lt;/strong&gt;. The company maximizes profits by selling a product that causes cancer in innocent victims. Meanwhile, farmers who are unaware of (or indifferent to) the pollution will actually reward the company by buying more of its cheaper, more effective product, further incentivizing the harmful behavior. Competitors who invest in making safer, non-toxic alternatives might lose out because their products are more expensive. &lt;strong&gt;This is where the government must step in, regulating or banning such harmful practices to protect public health.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;(Note 4)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all externalities require government intervention. Take, for example, small children on airplanes. They scream, kick the seat in front of them, and generally make the flight less enjoyable for everyone around them. Imagine being stuck on a 12-hour flight with a 5-year-old directly behind you and a 1-year-old beside you. Even if the ticket was free, you’d probably hesitate to take that seat. Here, parents don’t bear the full cost of traveling with their young ones; other passengers do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why doesn’t the government need to step in here? Because this is a problem the airline itself can address. It’s a manageable issue involving a relatively small group of people. For instance, airlines could designate seating for families with children under 5 in the back of the plane, grouping them together. They could also offer noise-cancelling headphones to other passengers during the flight. The key point is that government intervention isn’t necessary when companies can implement practical solutions on their own, and whenever possible, it’s better to let them handle it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2002, an electricity company in a small Ohio town started getting complaints from nearby residents about heavy pollution from its power plant. The 221 residents had every right to sue the company, but instead, the company decided to make it simple. They paid each resident about three times what their homes were worth in exchange for a promise not to sue for pollution-related damages. It cost the company $20 million, but it solved the problem quickly: no heavy government bureaucracy, no drawn-out lawsuits, just a clean and simple deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of solution was only possible because of the relatively small number of people involved in the externality. Private companies are not going to solve something like CO2 emissions on a national or global scale because those problems are far too big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s look at how the government can help with dealing with externalities. Sure, the government can ban harmful practices or chemicals outright, but sometimes there are better ways to change behavior. Take the Hummer, for example. The Hummer is incredibly inefficient when it comes to fuel consumption, yet some people still use it to go to the grocery store instead of driving something their Honda Civic. If the government wants to discourage people from buying/driving fuel-inefficient cars, what can they do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way is through taxes. This could mean a gas or emissions tax, a weight tax, or a combination of both. First, taxing limits the behavior since you probably will not want to drive a Hummer if it costs twice as much to fill up. Second, it raises revenue, which can be used to help cover the costs related to global warming, like investing more in R&amp;amp;D for alternative energy sources. Third, if people know they will pay for the extra weight and poor fuel efficiency, they will make different choices at the dealership. Thanks to competition in the free market, car manufacturers will respond by making vehicles that are lighter and more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, taxing externalities is not always a perfect solution. First of all, how do you determine the right amount of tax? Secondly, raising the cost of driving large SUVs and pickup trucks will mean that only those who value it most will continue to drive them. But we measure how much we value something by how much we are willing to pay for it, and the rich can always afford to pay more. So such a tax would unfairly disadvantage a poor contractor who is struggling to make ends meet but actually needs his pickup truck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to address this would be to use the revenue from those gas-guzzler taxes to offset taxes that hit the middle class the hardest, like payroll taxes. This way, the contractor might pay a bit more for his truck, but less to the IRS, which helps balance it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;positive-externality&quot;&gt;Positive Externality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also &lt;strong&gt;positive externalities: situations where an individual’s actions benefit others without any extra compensation.&lt;/strong&gt; For example, if my office has an absolutely amazing view that inspires me every day when I go to work, and it’s one of the main things that puts a smile on my face throughout the workday, I don’t need to send a check to the builders or the architect for providing that view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine I’m a small brick-and-mortar business owner in a small town. Someone decides to build an amusement park nearby. A few months later, new restaurants open up, residential homes are built, more people move in, and so on. Naturally, my shop will see more customers as a result, &lt;strong&gt;yet I won’t owe anyone a penny for the increased business I’m getting.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is exactly why governments offer subsidies for such investments.&lt;/strong&gt; Building something like an amusement park can bring value to an entire community—it creates jobs, attracts more businesses, and boosts the local economy. Since the builder isn’t directly compensated for all the additional benefits they create, the government might step in to provide incentives or subsidies to encourage these kinds of investments. This way, projects that benefit everyone are more likely to happen, even if the private gains aren’t enough on their own to make them worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;property-rights&quot;&gt;Property Rights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way the government smooths the rough edges of a free market is by enforcing property rights, including intellectual property (IP) and copyright laws, which are a form of property rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Napster as an example. Napster was one of the first peer-to-peer file-sharing platforms, which revolutionized how people accessed music in the early 2000s. However, it encountered serious legal difficulties due to copyright infringement. Bands like Metallica and artists like Dr. Dre filed lawsuits because Napster was facilitating the distribution of their copyrighted music without permission or compensation. Copyright laws exist to protect creators and ensure they are paid for their work, encouraging more creative output. Without such laws, artists and companies would be less likely to invest time and resources into creating new content if anyone could freely copy and distribute it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, consider the example of Pfizer and its patent on Viagra. This book was written in 2013, and back then, Pfizer held the patent on Viagra, allowing it to set the price at $7 per pill, despite the production cost being only a fraction of that. The patent, guaranteed by the government, meant no other company could legally copy Pfizer’s formula. Many may argue that this leads to inflated prices, but patents are crucial for encouraging innovation. Without the protection of a patent, other companies could immediately copy and sell Pfizer’s product, making it impossible for Pfizer to recover the hundreds of millions of dollars spent on R&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If companies couldn’t protect the products they spent years developing, why would anyone invest in costly and time-consuming processes like searching rainforests for plants with potential medical benefits? Intellectual property rights provide an incentive to innovate by ensuring that inventors and companies can profit from their discoveries, which ultimately benefits society with new and improved products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regulations&quot;&gt;Regulations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the previous section, governments create rules and regulations that help lower the cost of doing business in the private sector. They enforce contracts, crack down on fraud, and keep a sound currency circulating. Without these things, markets can’t function smoothly. Imagine trying to run a business without a stable dollar, or a way to enforce contracts when someone doesn’t hold up their end of the deal. This is where agencies like the SEC (protects investors from corporate fraud), FAA (safety while flying), FDA (safety of food and drugs), FBI (protection from crime), IRS (tax collection and enforcement), INS (immigration services and enforcement), and the U.S. Patent Office (protection for inventions) come in. They protect consumers, keep companies accountable, and make sure the playing field is fair enough that business can actually thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;free-rider-problem&quot;&gt;Free-Rider Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments also provide public goods. These are things that make us all better off but would not exist if we left them to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose I decide I want to buy an anti-missile system to protect myself from a belligerent neighboring country. I ask my neighbors if they want to pitch in. Most say no because they have a strong incentive to be “free riders”. If the system is built, they’ll benefit from it without having to pay a cent. In the end, the system doesn’t get built, even though it would have made us all safer if everyone had chipped in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A private company can’t force people to pay for these kinds of goods, no matter how much they use them or benefit from them. Think of a lighthouse, a public park, a radio signal, research in the Higgs Boson, or law enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s expand on law enforcement. Sure, you could hire a personal bodyguard, but they’ll only protect you from immediate threats. Who’s going to trace the gangs or potential criminals who may someday target you? Who’s handling counter-terrorism? Public goods like these require collective funding, which is why they’re provided by the government, not by private businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stop-blaming-the-government-for-everything&quot;&gt;Stop Blaming the Government for Everything&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government also redistributes wealth. It collects taxes from some citizens and provides benefits to others. Contrary to popular belief, most government benefits do not go to the poor; they go to the middle class in the form of Medicare and Social Security. But who decides how much the government should tax, and who should receive those benefits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this: which scenario is better for the overall state of the country? A society where everyone earns $25’000 (enough to cover basic necessities) or the status quo, where some Americans are incredibly wealthy, some are desperately poor, and the average income is around $48’000? The second scenario describes a larger economic pie, but with unequal slices. The first is a smaller pie, but more evenly divided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economics does not provide clear answers to philosophical questions like these. It cannot tell us whether taking a dollar from a billionaire to give to a struggling family is “right” or “wrong”. This is not a science, and sometimes there is not a single clear answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, every presidential administration, whether conservative or liberal, will find qualified economists who will support their ideological opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quotes-from-ch3&quot;&gt;Quotes from Ch.3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Liberals (in the American sense of the word) often ignore the fact that a growing pie, even if unequally divided, will almost always make even the small pieces larger. […] One historical reality is that government policies that ostensibly serve the poor can be ineffective or even counterproductive if they hobble the broader economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, conservatives often lithely assume that we should all rush out into the streets and cheer for any policy that makes the economy grow faster, neglecting the fact that there are perfectly legitimate intellectual grounds for supporting other policies, such as protecting the environment or redistributing income, that may diminish the overall size of the pie.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-4-government-and-the-economy-2&quot;&gt;Chapter 4: Government and the Economy 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If governments were inherently efficient, then government-heavy countries like North Korea and Cuba would be economic powerhouses, but they are clearly not, and they lag behind developed Western nations &lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;(Note 5)&lt;/a&gt;. While a government can effectively address externalities, it can also regulate an economy into stagnation. It can provide essential public goods, but it can also mismanage and waste tax revenue. It can redistribute wealth to help the disadvantaged, but it can also divert resources to the politically well-connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;public-vs-private-sector-roles&quot;&gt;Public vs. Private Sector Roles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything that private companies can do should be allowed to be done by them. For instance, the USPS held a monopoly on mail for years until UPS and FedEx built better delivery systems, creating more competition and improving service for everyone. But not everything belongs in private hands. The DMV (Department of Motor Vehicles), which issues driver’s licenses, is better left with the government. Private companies would have incentives to attract customers by issuing licenses to drivers who do not deserve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine the government running steel mills, coal mines, banks, hotels, or airlines. All the benefits of competition, like efficiency and innovation, would be lost, and citizens would be worse off. In the private sector, markets direct resources to where they are most valued, and money flows wherever the return is highest. In contrast, governments allocate resources based on political priorities. It is therefore no surprise that the USSR was the first to send a rocket into orbit. Even if the people would rather have had fresh vegetables or contraceptives, the government still chose to invest in their space program. In the worst case scenario, car plants don’t get built, students don’t get loans, and entrepreneurs don’t get funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regulatory-deception&quot;&gt;Regulatory Deception&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Market interventions can have significant consequences, and regulation is often one of the tools used. At worst, regulations can become a political weapon for well-connected firms to stifle their competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, nail salons in Illinois were thriving, with a remarkable 23% growth. But just as these new businesses were establishing themselves, a campaign suddenly emerged, calling for stricter licensing requirements for manicurists. Was this a response to consumer complaints or a wave of botched pedicures? Not quite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind this push was the Illinois Cosmetology Association, representing established spas and salons that wanted to cut off their competition. The target? New immigrant “entrants” who were opening salons and offering affordable services, threatening the profits of long-established businesses. By tightening licensing rules, these established salons could force new competition to face countless obstacles, while conveniently exempting themselves from the hassle. What appeared to be a campaign for higher standards was, in truth, a cleverly disguised strategy to dominate the market and stifle competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, &lt;strong&gt;countries that make starting a business difficult end up undermining both economic growth and quality standards&lt;/strong&gt;. In places like Canada and New Zealand, streamlined processes support new ventures, but countries like Mozambique and Bolivia impose months-long, costly procedures. And what do they get for all that regulation? Lower compliance with quality standards, not better. Instead of making things safer, these hurdles push businesses underground, away from oversight, and right into the hands of corruption. In the end, both consumers and the economy pay the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-laffer-curve&quot;&gt;The Laffer Curve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Laffer Curve is a concept in economics that illustrates the relationship between tax rates and government revenue. Proposed by economist Arthur Laffer, it suggests that there is an optimal tax rate somewhere between 0% and 100% that maximizes revenue. If taxes are too low, the government does not collect enough revenue, while excessively high taxes may pushe people to leave the country altogether or discourage them from working, reducing taxable income and thus revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During Ronald Reagan’s presidency, the administration adopted the principles behind the Laffer Curve, leading to significant tax cuts in the 1980s. The theory was that lower taxes would encourage people to work more, save, and invest, ultimately broadening the tax base and stimulating economic growth. For instance, if the tax rate is initially 50% with a tax base of $100 million, the government would collect $50 million in revenue. Now imagine the tax rate is reduced to 40%. With lower taxes, people are more motivated to work since they get to keep more of their earnings. Some may decide to work extra hours, and others might take on second jobs. As a result, the tax base grows to $110 million. The government now collects $44 million, which is less than before but still benefits from the additional economic activity that emerged due to increased incentives for work. This approach aimed to demonstrate how reducing the tax burden could partially offset revenue losses by promoting more economic output. Similar tax policies were later adopted during George W. Bush’s presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tax experts must consider these behavioral responses, such as how people adjust their work, saving, and investment habits, when estimating the effects of tax cuts or increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-goldilocks-zone&quot;&gt;The Goldilocks Zone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government should ideally find a balance in its role in the economy; it should neither control everything nor be completely absent. Somewhere between the extremes is the right level of involvement that ensures efficiency and welfare. If everything is left to the free market, we end up with businesses catering to luxury wants, like custom-made birthday cakes for dogs, simply because there is demand. But the free market does not always address essential needs, such as feeding the homeless. Finding the right balance is essential to support both economic growth and the well-being of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quotes-from-ch4&quot;&gt;Quotes from Ch.4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is an old joke, one of Ronald Reagan’s favorites, that goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Soviet woman is trying to buy a Lada, one of the cheap automobiles made in the former Soviet Union. The dealer tells her that there is a shortage of these cars, despite their reputation for shoddy quality. Still, the woman insists on placing an order. The dealer get out a large, dusty ledger and adds the woman’s name of the long waiting list. &lt;em&gt;“Come back two years from now on March 17th,”&lt;/em&gt; he says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The woman consults here calendar. &lt;em&gt;“Morning or afternoon?”&lt;/em&gt; she asks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What difference does it make?”&lt;/em&gt; the surly dealer replies. &lt;em&gt;“That’s two years from now!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The plumber is coming that day,”&lt;/em&gt; she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the USSR taught us anything, it is that monopoly stifles any need to be innovative or responsive to customers. And government is one very large monopoly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Markets work because resources flow to where they are valued most. Government regulation inherently interferes with that process. In the world painted by economics textbooks, entrepreneurs cross the road to earn higher profits. In the real world, government officials stand by the road and demand a toll, if they don’t block the crossing entirely. The entrepreneurial firm may have to obtain a license to cross the road, or have its vehicle emissions tested […], or prove […] that the workers crossing the road are U.S. citizens . Some of these regulations may make us better off. It’s good to have government officials blocking the road when the ‘entrepreneur’ is carrying seven kilos of cocaine. But every single regulation carries a cost, too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-5-the-economics-of-information&quot;&gt;Chapter 5: The Economics of Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-scholarship-programs-backfire&quot;&gt;When Scholarship Programs Backfire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Bill Clinton was running for president in 1992, he floated the idea of adding a new type of scholarship: the Hope Scholarship. The idea was simple: students could borrow money for college and then repay the loans after graduation with a percentage of their annual income rather than the usual fixed payments of principal plus interest. Graduates who went on to become investment bankers would owe more in student loans than graduates who counseled disadvantaged teens in poor neighborhoods. The plan was designed to address the concern that students graduating with large debts are forced to do well rather than do good. After all, it’s hard to become a teacher or a social worker after graduating with $75,000 in student loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, high and low earners would balance each other out, and the program would recoup its costs. Students who became brain surgeons would pay back more than average, while students who fought tropical diseases in Togo would pay less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the problem though: students know more about their future career plans than the university, so they can determine if a Hope Scholarship would be more or less expensive than a conventional loan. An aspiring doctor would avoid this scholarship, while the future kindergarten teacher would opt in. In the end, the program attracted predominantly low earners, and the repayment calculations had to be redone because there was now a new sample consisting mostly of low-income earners. The program was unable to recover its costs and quietly died down within five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;information-and-rational-discrimination-in-hiring&quot;&gt;Information and Rational Discrimination in Hiring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider a small law firm interviewing two job candidates, one male and one female, both recent Harvard Law graduates and equally qualified &lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;(Note 6)&lt;/a&gt;. If the “best” candidate is the one who will make the most money for the firm, then the rational choice would be to hire the man. The interviewer cannot ask about family plans but can infer that women are more likely to take paid maternity leave and may not return to work, leaving the firm with additional costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this certain? No. The male candidate may want to stay home, and the female candidate may not want children. But the firm makes decisions based on broad social trends, not individual cases. Is this fair? No. Is it legal? No. But the firm’s logic is economically rational, even if it may offend our sensibilities and violate federal law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is there is a simple solution: a generous but refundable maternity package. Women keep the benefit if they return to work and return it if they do not. This reduces the firm’s concern about paying benefits unnecessarily and makes them more willing to hire women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employers sometimes make decisions based on statistical trends that may be rational for them but lead to unfair outcomes. For example, suppose an employer dislikes hiring people with criminal records but doesn’t have access to that information. He may discriminate against black male applicants (28% of whom have been incarcerated) over white males (4%). All the employer wants to know is whether the person in front of him has a record, which means specific information trumps broader statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policies aimed at helping ex-offenders by suppressing criminal record information can also have unintended consequences. In theory, access to criminal background checks should reduce discrimination against black men without criminal records. Economists found that firms conducting background checks are more likely to hire African-American men, especially among employers with aversions to hiring people with records. Without access to that information, employers may rely on racial stereotypes, worsening disparities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;branding-as-a-solution-to-information-gaps&quot;&gt;Branding as a Solution to Information Gaps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firms often create their own mechanisms to solve information-related problems. For example, every McDonald’s burger is the same, whether in Mexico or in Ohio. Before we had Google reviews to tell us about the opening hours and quality of a small mom-and-pop fast food restaurant, there was a lot of missing information. McDonald’s solved that issue for themselves by being consistent across all locations. If someone is driving on the highway, they are hungry, and they see a McDonald’s sign, they know it will be open, the bathroom will be clean, and they might even know exactly how many pickles will be in their Big Mac. This predictability makes people more likely to choose McDonald’s over a random restaurant they’ve never heard of, even if that restaurant might be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense for companies to spend a lot of money building an identity for their products. This is what branding is. In a world where consumers must make assumptions, branding helps provide an element of trust that is necessary for a complex economy to function. Modern business requires that we conduct major transactions with people we have never met. Therefore, it comes as no surprise that businesses routinely advertise their longevity with phrases like “Since 1927”, essentially saying, “We wouldn’t still be here if we ripped off our customers”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you won the lottery and are now looking for an investment adviser. The first firm you visit has a nice marble lobby, high-quality wood paneling on the walls, original Impressionist paintings, and executives wearing custom handmade Italian suits, fitted to perfection. Do you think: (1) “My fees will pay for all this very nice stuff, what a ripoff!” or (2) “Wow, this firm must be extremely successful, and I hope they will take me on as a client”. If you’re not convinced that the answer is the latter, imagine you go to another adviser, and he works in a shabby office with flickering lights, mismatched furniture, and computers from the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marble and the handmade suits say absolutely nothing about their work. However, they are signals that reassure us that the firm is top-notch. As the author put it, “They are to markets what a peacock’s bright feathers are to a prospective mate: a good sign in a world of imperfect information”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What constitutes a “good sign” can also be cultural. For example, in some parts of Asia, firms show their wealth and prestige by having air-conditioned offices, kept so cold that some workers use space heaters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quotes-from-ch5&quot;&gt;Quotes from Ch.5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the world of Econ 101, all parties have “perfect information.” The graphs are neat and tidy; consumers and producers know everything they could possibly want to know. The world outside of Econ 101 is more interesting, albeit messier. A state patrolman who has pulled over a 1990 Grand Am with a broken taillight on a deserted stretch of Florida highway does not have perfect information. Nor does a young family looking for a safe and dependable nanny, or an insurance company seeking to protect itself from the extraordinary costs of HIV/AIDS. Information matters. Economists study what we do with it, and, sometimes more important, what we do without it”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-6-productivity-and-human-capital&quot;&gt;Chapter 6: Productivity and Human Capital&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-capital&quot;&gt;Human Capital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the root causes of poverty, and why do so many people struggle to escape it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take Bill Gates as a case study. Any discussion about why he has significantly more wealth than someone sleeping under a bridge must include “human capital”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the author defines it, “Human capital is the sum total of skills embodied within an individual: education, intelligence, charisma, creativity, work experience, entrepreneurial vigor, even the ability to throw a baseball fast”. Human capital also includes qualities like perseverance and honesty. If all of your assets, such as your job, money, and home, were taken away, human capital is what remains. Bill Gates, for instance, would still fare well because companies would immediately seek him out for roles as a consultant or CEO. Similarly, Tiger Woods could win a golf tournament if someone handed him a set of clubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In market economies, the price of a skill is determined not by its social value but by its scarcity. Robert Solow, the 1987 Nobel Prize-winning economist, was once asked if it bothered him that Roger Clemens, who was pitching for the Red Sox at the time, earned far more than he did. Solow’s response was simple: “No. There are a lot of good economists, but there is only one Roger Clemens”. Clemens’ skills as a star pitcher were rarer, which is why he earned so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skills required to ask, “Would you like fries with that?” are not scarce. Millions of people in America could fill that role, so it remains a minimum-wage job. Meanwhile, a top trial lawyer’s skills are rare, allowing them to charge $500 an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might say that people are poor in America because they can’t find good jobs. But that is the symptom, not the cause. The deeper issue is often a lack of skills or human capital. The poverty rate for high school dropouts in America is 12 times higher than for college graduates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a healthy economy also plays a role. It was easier to find a job in 2018 than in 1975 or 1932. A rising tide does indeed lift all boats, but that high tide will not turn a valet parking attendant into a college professor. Investment in human capital is what makes that transformation possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-lump-of-labor-fallacy&quot;&gt;The Lump of Labor Fallacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The lump of labor fallacy is the mistaken belief that there is a fixed amount of work available in the economy, and that increasing the number of workers decreases the amount of work available for everyone else, or vice-versa.&lt;/em&gt;” (Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/l/lump-of-labour-fallacy.asp&quot;&gt;Investopedia&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the lump of labor fallacy may seem intuitive, it is a common misconception worth clarifying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, let’s think about over the last 40 years. The entire Internet sector was created out of thin air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-20th century, millions of women have entered the workforce. Did they take away work from men? Obviously not. Similarly, immigration has introduced new workers across multiple sectors without reducing the overall availability of jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were there short-term displacements? Of course. We all see an increase in competition as the supply of labor grows, as we have to compete with new entrants to the labor force. But as mentioned in chapter 2, this is all part of the “creative destruction” process. In the long-term, we are all better off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a farming community where every family owns land and produces just enough food for themselves. They have no surplus harvest and no additional farmland, which makes it seem like there’s no room for another worker. Every family has to teach their own children, make their own clothes, repair their own tractors, etc. Now, imagine a guy gets dropped off a bus into this village, but he has no skills. Since there’s no more land, this guy has nothing to do. This village has “no jobs”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine “guy number 2” gets off the bus into this village, but this guy has a PhD in agronomy. His research was in developing a new kind of plow that improves corn yields. He trades his plow to farmers in exchange for a small share of their harvests. In this scenario, the agronomist can live in the village on infertile land and still support himself, while the farmers have more food for themselves. This village has now created a new job: plow salesman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later, a teacher arrives in the village. Now, instead of the parents teaching their children, they can give that job to the teacher. Now the farmers have even more time to do what they do best: farming. They are growing more food than they can eat themselves, and so they now have a surplus of it, which they can “spend” on the agronomist and on the teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what started with a village that has no more room for an extra person suddenly has “space”. And this space was created. After some time, there will be novelists, firefighters, engineers, and politicians, and it won’t be a village anymore, but a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, over time, someone will come up with a better plow design that produces better yields than the one that “guy number 2” came up with, and so “guy number 2” will see his revenue decrease as farmers buy the better product. This is unfortunate for “guy number 2”, but this is part of the process. One person will lose their job, but overall, the city will be better off because of the new technology: farmers will get better yields, and so they will have even more to “spend”. One day, some other person with a PhD might develop new hybrid seeds, and the farmers will spend their surplus on that, which will, in turn, make them yet again even richer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the point of this exercise is to show that the farmers get richer, which creates demand for new jobs elsewhere in the economy, since the village “can afford it”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-capital--everything-else&quot;&gt;Human Capital &amp;gt; Everything Else&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your country could be sitting on oil and diamonds, but there seems to be a lack of correlation between natural resources and standard of living. Meanwhile, there seems to be a positive correlation between a country’s level of human capital and its standard of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries like Japan and Switzerland have barely any natural resources, yet they are some of the wealthiest in the world. Meanwhile, countries like Nigeria have lots of oil, but still have a poor quality of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because of productivity. America is rich because Americans are productive. They work less and produce more than ever before. Work hours have come down from 3100 hours to 1730 hours per year, while real GDP (an inflation-adjusted measure of how much each person produces, on average) has gone from $4800 to $40000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And productivity is another reason why not all jobs are leaving the US and heading to Mexico or Vietnam or Bangladesh, where labor is much cheaper. A worker who costs a tenth as much but produces a tenth as much is not a bargain. But in industries such as garment manufacturing, producing footwear, or assembling basic goods like basketballs and t-shirts, where workers may be half as productive but cost a tenth as much, that’s a good deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;revenge-of-the-nerds&quot;&gt;Revenge of the Nerds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that in 1979, the top 1% of Americans earned 9% of the nation’s total income, while by 2013, it was 16%? Human capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human capital has become more important and therefore better rewarded. This is evident among college graduates, who in 1980 earned 40% more than high school graduates, while by 2013, they earned 80% more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society is evolving in ways that favor skilled workers. For example, the shift toward computers in nearly every industry benefits workers who either have computer skills or are smart enough to learn them on the job. Technology makes smart workers more productive while making low-skilled workers redundant. ATMs replaced bank tellers, self-serve pumps replaced gas station attendants, and automated assembly lines replaced workers doing mindless, repetitive jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, globalization and international trade put low-skilled workers in greater competition with other low-skilled workers around the globe. It’s hard to ask for $15/hour when Nike can pay workers $1/day to make shoes in a Vietnamese sweatshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quotes-from-ch6&quot;&gt;Quotes from Ch.6&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Technology displaces workers in the short run but does not lead to mass unemployment in the long run. Rather, we become richer, which creates demand for new jobs elsewhere in the economy. Of course, educated workers fare much better than uneducated workers in this process. THey are more versatile in a fast-changing economy, making them more likely to be left standing after a bout of creative destruction.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Families who live in public housing on the South Side of Chicago are not poor because Bill Gates lives in a big house. They are poor despite the fact that Bill Gates Lives in a big house. […] Bill Gates did not take their pie away; he did not stand in the way of their success or benefit from their misfortunes. Rather, his vision and talent created an enormous amount of wealth that not everybody got to share. There is a crucial distinction between a world in which Bill Gates gets rich by stealing other people’s crops and a world in which he gets rich by growing his own enormous food supply that he shares with some people and not others.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By selfish, I mean we all seek our own happiness, and the path we take varies for each of us. Some people might be happy by purchasing a new car, while others are happier when they help someone cross the street, or volunteer somewhere. The latter have value as well, even if not monetary. This is the concept of utility in economics: the total satisfaction or benefit derived from consuming a good or service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-1-the-power-of-markets&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve only heard two good arguments thus far in defense of communism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, external influence from capitalist countries. I mean, the CIA went nuts shortly after its creation in 1947. Iran 1953, Guatemala 1954, Congo 1960, Cuba 1961. Bribing politicians, funding protests, funding labor movements to undermine governments. Setting up a fake radio station pretending to be coming from that country, broadcasting false reports of uprisings and protests (this happened in Guatemala). Providing equipment and training to exiles and rebel groups. These are the lengths to which the U.S. and its allies went to ensure that communism didn’t gain a foothold in those countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the U.S. simply did what was necessary to protect its strategic interests; they did what they believed was essential to maintain their position as the world’s superpower. If it’s the middle of the Cold War and you know that Congo has rich deposits of Uranium, you’re going to make sure it stays out of communist hands &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xSyEnnGR4ec&quot;&gt;(video explaining the Congo situation)&lt;/a&gt;. The stakes were global, and they played the game accordingly, pulling whatever strings necessary to tilt the balance of power in their favor. I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mwyjlmEAcYM&quot;&gt;this video as well detailing the meddling of Chile and Nicaragua&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying the USSR didn’t engage in the same interferences, but it’s hard to determine the effectiveness of a system if the world’s superpower keeps meddling in your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And second&lt;/strong&gt;, let’s all remember the historical context in which the USSR emerged. The USSR, for example, started as a largely agrarian society already devastated by World War I (2 million soldiers killed), followed by a brutal civil war (~10 million deaths). Just as they were developing, World War II killed 27 million Soviet citizens (as well as displacing millions more and destroying industrial and agricultural zones). They were essentially trying to industrialize and build a new economic system while simultaneously recovering from multiple catastrophes and playing catch-up with more developed nations. How much did US benefit from having the two largest oceans surrounding it as natural protection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to note that I’ve heard people claim that Communism has killed 100 million people. How stupid or intellectually dishonest must people be to make these analyses? I’ve heard claims that Stalin alone killed 40 million people. The truth is that Stalin killed ~1 million during The Great Terror of 1937 (a political purge against dissidents), ~1.5 million through his gulags, ~1 million during deportations of ethnic groups (mainly during WW2), and ~4 million Ukrainians during the 1932-1933 Holodomor. The only way to reach that 40 million figure is by including all the war deaths, which you cannot fairly blame on communism itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even the deaths through Stalin, can you blame it on communism itself? I haven’t looked into the link between authoritarianism and communism, so I’m not sure. But I remember enjoying reading Animal Farm by George Orwell. Really good book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quick note: After Stalin’s death in 1953, the level of state violence in the USSR decreased significantly. Under Khrushchev (1953-1964), most gulags were shut down, political prisoners were released, purges ended, and no more mass deportations. Things remained authoritarian, but to a much lesser extend with less severe consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And China I’ve heard killed 60 million people. The truth is that during the Great Leap Forward (1958-1962), Mao’s attempt to rapidly industrialize caused the largest famine in human history, killing somewhere between 15-25 million people. This happened because farmers were forced to make steel instead of growing food, and local officials lied about grain production to meet quotas which was devastating because these fake numbers meant the government kept taking and exporting grain while people were actually starving. They literally couldn’t fix the problem because no one knew how bad it really was. While this disaster wasn’t caused by communist ideology directly, it was made possible by the total control of a communist system where no one could oppose these policies or safely report the truth. Then during the Cultural Revolution (1966-1976), another 750,000 to 1.5 million died from direct violence through Red Guard persecution of “class enemies” and forced relocations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, that’s a lot of deaths, and it shows something important about communist systems: when they fail, they fail big. Because when you have total state control and no one can speak up or change course, bad policies don’t just cause problems, they cause catastrophes with no brakes to stop them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just saying that communism wouldn’t necessarily succeed without external pressures outside of its control (the first two points I mentioned about the USSR). Bureaucratic inefficiencies are a problem, concentration of power is another, and so it economic calculation (which basically means prices can’t naturally adjust to reflect true scarcity and demand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#quotes-from-ch1&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the case when you’re a first-time buyer, not an investor. If you’re an investor and your real estate agent knows you’ll be buying and selling properties throughout your life, then their incentives align with yours. It’s in their best interest to look out for you because they know you’ll be a repeat customer. That’s when a partnership forms; one where your success becomes their success too. In the long run, this kind of relationship is what will make the agent the most money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#misaligned-incentives-in-the-corporate-world&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A classic example of negative externalities is the “Great American Streetcar Scandal” of the mid-20th century. Between 1938 and 1950, General Motors, along with Firestone Tire, Standard Oil, and others, systematically bought and dismantled electric streetcar systems in about 25 cities including St. Louis, Baltimore, Los Angeles, and Oakland, replacing them with GM buses. While this was profitable for the companies involved, it had massive negative externalities: increased urban pollution, higher transportation costs for citizens, and the destruction of efficient public transit infrastructure that had served communities for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conspiracy fundamentally changed how American cities looked and functioned. Instead of having dense, walkable neighborhoods connected by streetcars (like many European cities today), cities kept expanding outwards with endless rows of single-family homes far from city centers. Living in these new suburban areas made car ownership essential, leading to more traffic, pollution, and longer commute times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This case perfectly illustrates how private market actions can create lasting negative impacts on society, especially when those decisions reshape infrastructure in ways that force certain consumption patterns (in this case, making car ownership practically mandatory for most Americans).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#negative-externalities&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, these countries have typically faced significant external pressure and economic sanctions from powerhouses like the United States, which have severely affected their economies. For example, Cuba has faced a U.S. embargo for decades, which has drastically limited its ability to trade and access vital resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-4-government-and-the-economy-2&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-1&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to note that (like most of the examples in this book) this example of how firms make decisions under uncertainty, while supported by economic logic, is a generalization. It’s important to note that real-life situations are complex, and the book uses hypothetical scenarios to illustrate economic principles rather than to provide specific case studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#information-and-rational-discrimination-in-hiring&quot;&gt;Return&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Books" /><category term="Economics" /><summary type="html">This is Part 1 of my detailed summary of “Naked Economics: Undressing the Dismal Science”. It covers foundational topics in economics, focusing on markets, incentives, government intervention, information, and human capital.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Bitcoin Whitepaper: My Initial Thoughts</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/My-thourghts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bitcoin Whitepaper: My Initial Thoughts" /><published>2023-04-17T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2023-04-17T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/My-thourghts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/My-thourghts/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-is-the-fifth-article-in-a-series-where-my-goal-is-to-understand-the-blockchain-nfts-and-the-related-technologies&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the fifth article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we move any further on &lt;strong&gt;facts&lt;/strong&gt;, I wanted to share some of my &lt;strong&gt;thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;/concerns so far about blockchain and Bitcoin, based on my current understanding of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my understanding (not just by reading the whitepaper), Bitcoin is a digital asset used as a store of value (rather than being a currency). Similar to gold, but without any industry applications… but it’s much more divisible. And portable. And hideable… but at the same time it can’t be used in jewelry, nor in electronics, nor in dentistry, nor in aerospace (gold is used to coat certain satellite components to protect them from solar radiation, pretty cool eh?). &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin. It’s value comes from the fact that there are other people who would buy it. If the price goes down to 20k, there will be people who will think “that’s a steal”. If the value goes up to 60k, there will be people who will start to sell. Maybe in a near-distance future, the price range won’t be ±40k, but will start to settle down. But who knows. Because honestly, how do we put a number on this protocol? A bitcoin is definitely worth something, but to put an exact number on it makes no sense. While we can read a company’s balance sheet, look at its expected sales, etc. and deduce an approximate valuation, it’s a bit harder to put a number on transaction rules which are enforced by thousands of nodes around the world, all using up electrical power in order to sustain the system full of strangers whom they’ve never met before. It’s truly a beautiful invention, but it’s hard to pinpoint its intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense you can argue that its intrinsic value is meant to slightly keep increasing due to its (slightly) deflationary nature. However, that assumes that interest levels (of the people, not the monetary policy tool) stay constant, or better yet, rise, among the general population. And that’s not too hard to see happen. Since once you get Bitcoin, you can’t “un-get” it. Once you see the beauty of it, you can’t unsee it. The true fan club (and not those people in it to make a quick buck) can only grow (this growth can be stunted by external factors such as governmental regulations, as mentioned in the next paragraph).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite all this positive talk, and despite me thinking that Bitcoin is a beautiful creation, I think that a big part of Bitcoin’s and other cryptocurrencies price appreciation is due to hype and people trying to make a quick profit, RATHER THAN being tied to a fundamental demand for the underlying technology (“market value” vs “intrinsic value”). It’s really dependant on very superficial factors such as media coverage, celebrity endorsements, overall economic conditions, and government regulation; the first three having a more short-term effect, and the latter having a stronger impact on the value of Bitcoin I’d argue (if the government makes it illegal to transact in bitcoin tomorrow, I doubt many people will dabble in it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also don’t buy Satoshi’s big idea that middlemen are all that bad. He made a big deal about how “a seller can get scammed by a buyer if the seller sends the product and the buyer disputes the purchase with the bank leaving the seller without both the item and the money”. I’m not saying they’re perfect, but I’d argue that most people would like to have an assurance that IF they forget their password to their account, they can recover it. IF they mispell the email address for an e-transfer, the bank can cancel the transaction. And sometimes, you just need to sue the person you are transacting with. As a law-abiding citizen, you would prefer to live in a country where the law is applicable at all times. Such a regulatory environment cannot have roots within a blockchain. Governments and centralized authorities will always have a place in our world. (I guess this is not an attack on Bitcoin per se anymore, it’s more about the idea that blockchain technology does have it’s limitations in use cases).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just a few words about the blockchain: while blockchain technology offers many benefits, it is important to recognize its limitations when it comes to storing sensitive information. While the transactions on the Bitcoin network may seem “random” and hidden,  they are pseudonymous, meaning that the identity of the users behind the transactions is not directly revealed, but can be deduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Facebook-Cambridge Analytica scandal taught us anything, it’s that ordinary civilians are uncomfortable and frustrated with how their personal data is shared left and right without their consent. People clearly value privacy and control over their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we expand blockchain’s reach into other aspects of our lives, then anyone would be able to read/estimate how much money we have, where we visit, who we chat with, which airlines we use, which movies we watch, so on and so forth. Would you rather Netflix see and analyze your watch pattern, feed the data into their AI tools and show you new movie recommendations, or would you rather have anyone with access to the blockchain see which movie you watched yesterday? Because at the end of the day, everything you do on the blockchain leaves a permanent mark and can be traced back to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-2023-04-28&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 2023-04-28&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bitcoin whitepaper doesn’t implicitly talk about this, but it’s still something that came up in my mind: what happens if a fake transaction is broadcasted? What stops me from saying that Jonny is sending me 10 bitcoins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m writing it, the answer is pretty clear: I can’t pretend to be Jonny. The previous owner of those 10 bitcoins has to sign and approve the transaction using his private key, which I don’t have access to. If I were to broadcast such a message out to the network, sure the nodes will pick it up, but they go through steps to validate a transaction; they don’t just turn a blind eye to the details and add everything they get to the block that they’re working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nodes in the Bitcoin network are programmed to verify the validity of every transaction they receive, and they do this by checking that the transaction meets certain criteria, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The transaction is properly formatted with the correct syntax and data structure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The transaction inputs are valid (i.e. they have not already been spent)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The transaction outputs are valid (i.e. they do not exceed the inputs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The transaction is signed with the correct private key(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a node receives a transaction that fails to meet any of these criteria, it will reject the transaction and not include it in the block. And if a miner (for example, me) does try to include an invalid transaction in their block &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;, other nodes will reject the block thanks to the proof-of-work concept: the longest chain is the one that is the real chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’d argue that that is a big part on why gold’s value is pretty stable and people consider it to be a safe investment. If ever people decide that gold isn’t valuable (for whatever reason), and you have money in gold, well then in the worst case scenario, there are uses in various industries for this material, so there will always be some demand for it. It’s relatively safe because its value will never be 0, as will likely always be demand for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think we can say that with certainty about Bitcoin. Its future is not as clear. Blockchain technology will likely thrive and we will keep finding uses for it, but Bitcoin, it’s hard to tell. If we enter a recession, will people be buying Bitcoin? I don’t know. But now, if we enter a recession, will people be buying gold? Yes, probably. Either NASA will be working on a new satellite, and if a cut in NASA’s budget occurs, well then people will need it in their teeth, and if not, then I can guarantee that people will still be buying phones and electronics with gold in them. Industry applications are not that large for gold, but that’s enough to build confidence in people about its value. Other than industry uses, which are critical for technological advancement and the betterment of our lives, there is also jewelery. Gold is very much ingrained in certain cultures, such as in Hindu weddings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We value what others value. If you’re in prison, and you don’t smoke, you will still accept a cigarette as a form of payment because you know that the entire cohort of section B smoke, and you know they will always want cigarettes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, I don’t even think that I’ll be able to add a fake transaction, even to my block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To participate in the Bitcoin network, I would need to follow the rules of the protocol, including verifying the validity of transactions. Having 51% of the computing power would give me the ability to create a longer blockchain and potentially conduct a double-spend attack, but it would not give me the ability to bypass the transaction verification process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html">This is the fifth article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bitcoin Part 1.1: Continuing Reading the Whitepaper</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin Part 1.1: Continuing Reading the Whitepaper" /><published>2023-04-13T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2023-04-13T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper2/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-is-the-fourth-article-in-a-series-where-my-goal-is-to-understand-the-blockchain-nfts-and-the-related-technologies&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the fourth article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-proof-of-work&quot;&gt;4. Proof-of-Work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous section, we saw how one block’s identity is determined by the previous block, and the previous block’s identity is determined by the block before it, so on and so forth. All blocks are linked, and a change in a block from the past will cause an error in the hash values of all the future blocks. Ok good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what if I am someone with malicious intentions. Going back to the “corporate” example, where a company will publish all its log files at the end of a day, and combine those into a block and do the same thing for the rest of the workweek. If it is Friday, and I want to go back to Monday’s records and change something there. If we are using timestamping, as we discussed, if I change something on Monday, then the hash values of Tuesday’s, Wednesday’s, Thursday’s and Friday’s blocks will change, and the whole system will break. So what I can do, before anyone has the time to check that I broke the system, is I can recalculate the hash values of all the blocks following Monday. Because in reality, calculating a hash value of something takes less than a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to make this harder, Satoshi introduces the concept of “proof-of-work”. The main idea here is that in order to add/modify a block, it cannot be easy. It must be hard. To make a link between two blocks should not be as simple as running a hash function once. So if I change something on Monday, therefore breaking all the links going up to Friday, it will be hard for me to recalculate everything in a way that it works mathematically. It will be hard for me to go to other people, and tell them “I swear, this is the right sequence of blocks, not that one”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is a problem that arises with decentralization. Because if a central authority was running the show, then they’d just have one chain. Only they have access to it, and so there is one truth. However, when dealing with people all around the world, anyone can come forth and say “this person owes me this much, look at this chain!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\btc\img3.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s say we have a transaction Tx. A transaction will replace what we called “items” in section 3. Also, inside the block, we’re going to have the hash of the previous block, and a “nonce” (“Number used ONCE”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-proof-of-work-involves-scanning-for-a-value-that-when-hashed-such-as-with-sha-256-the-hash-begins-with-a-certain-number-of-zero-bits-the-average-work-required-is-exponential-in-the-number-of-zero-bits-required-and-can-be-verified-by-executing-a-single-hash&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The proof-of-work involves scanning for a value that when hashed, such as with SHA-256, the hash begins with a [certain] number of zero bits. The average work required is exponential in the number of zero bits required and can be verified by executing a single hash.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We concatenante all the transaction with the hash of the previous block, and with the nonce. We then take the hash value of that. The proof-of-work system asks us to find the value of the nonce such that the resulting hash will start with, say, ten 0’s. This is not easy to do; out of the 64 hexadecimal characters, the first 10 must all be 0’s. Once you find a nonce which will yield that result, then you have PROVEN that you have done the WORK. Furthermore, others can verify that you have done the work very easily; all they have to do is take the nonce that you found, plug it in, calculate the resulting hash, and if they get a hash where the first 10 characters are all 0’s, then they have verified your work. &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;for-our-timestamp-network-we-implement-the-proof-of-work-by-incrementing-a-nonce-in-the-block-until-a-value-is-found-that-gives-the-blocks-hash-the-required-zero-bits-once-the-cpu-effort-has-been-expended-to-make-it-satisfy-the-proof-of-work-the-block-cannot-be-changed-without-redoing-the-work-as-later-blocks-are-chained-after-it-the-work-to-change-the-block-would-include-redoing-all-the-blocks-after-it&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;For our timestamp network, we implement the proof-of-work by incrementing a nonce in the block until a value is found that gives the block’s hash the required zero bits. Once the CPU effort has been expended to make it satisfy the proof-of-work, the block cannot be changed without redoing the work. As later blocks are chained after it, the work to change the block would include redoing all the blocks after it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, “bitcoin mining devices” are just calculating hashes all day long (simply changing the nonce each time), and once they get a winning hash, they announce it. The first to find a correct nonce wins! It’s not too different from playing the lottery if you think about it. And just like if you buy more tickets, your odds of winning increase, a node/miner (person participating in the blockchain) has more chances of finding the right nonce if he/she has more CPU power. As Satoshi writes, “&lt;em&gt;Proof-of-work is essentially one-CPU-one-vote&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-majority-decision-is-represented-by-the-longest-chain-which-has-the-greatest-proof-of-work-effort-invested-in-it-if-a-majority-of-cpu-power-is-controlled-by-honest-nodes-the-honest-chain-will-grow-the-fastest-and-outpace-any-competing-chains-to-modify-a-past-block-an-attacker-would-have-to-redo-the-proof-of-work-of-the-block-and-all-blocks-after-it-and-then-catch-up-with-and-surpass-the-work-of-the-honest-nodes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The majority decision is represented by the longest chain, which has the greatest proof-of-work effort invested in it. If a majority of CPU power is controlled by honest nodes, the honest chain will grow the fastest and outpace any competing chains. To modify a past block, an attacker would have to redo the proof-of-work of the block and all blocks after it and then catch up with and surpass the work of the honest nodes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say there is a group of malevolent miners (nodes) (people who are trying to find a right nonce) who control more than 51% of the total computing power (a.k.a. the hash rate) of the network. Then what this group can do is create an alternative chain of blocks (with a different transaction history), mine those faster than the rest of the “good” miners are mining their legitimate chain, and then once the fake chain is longer than the legitimate chain, everyone on the network will adopt the longer chain. This is how the proof-of-work system works: the chain which has the most work put into it will be the one that the nodes agree is the legitimate chain. This is called the 51% attack, and it is considered to be a serious threat to the security and integrity of the Bitcoin network, but it is also increasingly difficult and expensive to carry out as the network grows and more participants join.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-network&quot;&gt;5. Network&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not talk about this “P2P network”. There are clear steps that the network follows when Ann wants to send Bob some bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\btc\img4.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To reiterate, Ann will broadcast to every node that she is connected with, and all those nodes will share the transaction with all the nodes that they are connected with, so on and so forth until every node on the network is up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nodes are constantly on the lookout for transactions, because they need to fill up their block so that they can start looking for a corresponding nonce.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each node works on finding the nonce (by trying nonces and calculating the hash).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once a node finds a nonce for its block, it will broadcast the block to other nodes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Nodes accept the block only if all transactions in it are valid and not already spent”. The details on this one are trickier &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;, but essentially, all other nodes will validate the block, and if valid…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They will add this block to their version of the blockchain and continue the process, collecting transactions from nodes and building a block to hopefully eventually add to the chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;nodes-always-consider-the-longest-chain-to-be-the-correct-one-and-will-keep-working-on-extending-it-if-two-nodes-broadcast-different-versions-of-the-next-block-simultaneously-some-nodes-may-receive-one-or-the-other-first-in-that-case-they-work-on-the-first-one-they-received-but-save-the-other-branch-in-case-it-becomes-longer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Nodes always consider the longest chain to be the correct one and will keep working on extending it. If two nodes broadcast different versions of the next block simultaneously, some nodes may receive one or the other first. In that case, they work on the first one they received, but save the other branch in case it becomes longer.”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that as a node on the network, just because a block has been broadcasted and added to the blockchain, doesn’t mean that it is trustworthy. Instead, you should wait for several new blocks to be added on top of it. If, after a while, you haven’t heard of any longer chains of blocks which doesn’t include the block in question, well then you can trust that this block is part of the same chain that every other node is working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-incentive&quot;&gt;6. Incentive&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, why would anyone put up with running a node? Why should I spend money to buy computer hardware, or an ASIC (Application-Specific Integrated Circuit) miner, and spend money on electricity, in order to validate blocks on the blockchain? As it turns out, there is an incentive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you add a block to the “legitimate” chain, you are rewarded with bitcoin. The first transaction of every block is not “Ann paying Bob for guitar lessons”, no. The first transaction noted on every block in the blockchain has always and will always (until we run out of bitcoins to mine) be a gift from the Bitcoin network to the node which added that block to the blockchain. Once we reach the cap of 21 million bitcoins, then the nodes running the system will be gifted in another form: transaction fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, this gift awarded to the miner of a block is 6.25 bitcoins. 4 years ago it was 12.5 btc, 4 years before that it was 25 btc, and 4 years before that it was 50 btc. Sometime in 2024, the reward will be 3.125 btc. The dates are fuzzy because the halving occurs after 210’000 blocks have been added to the blockchain, and that occurs approximately every 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the further we go in time, yes, there are more nodes on the network, all competing to mine the next block, but also the reward you get for doing the work is less and less (that of course depends on the price of 1 bitcoin, so not completely true). The idea, from my understanding, is to limit the introduction of new coins, so that as demand increases, supply doesn’t increase as fast, and this leads to the price increase of every bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;7-reclaiming-disk-space&quot;&gt;7. Reclaiming Disk Space&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea here is that if we have a coin that’s moving from one owner to the next, we do not need to store every single transactions’s hash. What matters at the end is who owns the coin. If Ann pays Bob 1 bitcoin, and then a week later Bob pays Charlie that same bitcoin, well in order to make sure the system is intact and everyone has access to the coins that they own, we don’t need to know that Ann used to own that coin last week… at least not directly. This information can be deducted, if need be, thanks to the Merkel tree (a.k.a. “hash tree”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\btc\img5.png&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tree has a root node (the “Merkle root”), and this root node will be a hash representing all of the transactions in a block. There is no need for nodes on the network to store every transaction anymore. And by combining all transaction in this manner, we save disk space for every node. And all this while still maintaining our tamper-proof property (if I go back a few blocks and change one transaction, the “root hash” will be different, and my block will be invalidated, causing a ripple effect onto the following blocks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To hit the point home, in the image above, on the left, we have a block with 4 transactions. The Merkle tree is formed by concatenating the hashes of 2 subsequent transactions, and then repeating that with the hashes created, going up in the tree, until there is nothing left to combine; at that point, all the transactions are combined and summarized by the root hash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image on the right shows what happens if will never need to reference transactions 0 1 and 2 ever again, so we remove them and store their hashes instead. The hashes of Tx0 and Tx1 can be condensed together to save further space. All in all, instead of storing 4 transactions, we are now storing 2 hashes and 1 transaction (Tx3); that’s 3 items instead of four transactions. It doesn’t seem like a big deal when dealing with 4 transactions, but in reality, a block on the Bitcoin blockchain today holds, on average, 2000 transactions. So while 25% of 4 items is only 1, 25% of 2000 items is 500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what Vitalik Buterin had to say in the Ethereum whitepaper about the use of Merke Trees in Bitcoin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-merkle-tree-protocol-is-arguably-essential-to-long-term-sustainability-a-full-node-in-the-bitcoin-network-one-that-stores-and-processes-the-entirety-of-every-block-takes-up-about-15-gb-of-disk-space-in-the-bitcoin-network-as-of-april-2014-and-is-growing-by-over-a-gigabyte-per-month-currently-this-is-viable-for-some-desktop-computers-and-not-phones-and-later-on-in-the-future-only-businesses-and-hobbyists-will-be-able-to-participate&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The Merkle tree protocol is arguably essential to long-term sustainability. A “full node” in the Bitcoin network, one that stores and processes the entirety of every block, takes up about 15 GB of disk space in the Bitcoin network as of April 2014, and is growing by over a gigabyte per month. Currently, this is viable for some desktop computers and not phones, and later on in the future only businesses and hobbyists will be able to participate.”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;8-simplified-payment-verification&quot;&gt;8. Simplified Payment Verification&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of the Merkle Tree ties in very closely with SPV because they both talk about efficiency. Section 7 showed us that nodes don’t need to store all the data on all the previous blocks in the bloclchain. This section talks about how if you are a node on the network, you can participate in the network without knowing all the details of past transactions. This is useful for systems which are low on resources, such as a smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-user-only-needs-to-keep-a-copy-of-the-block-headers-of-the-longest-proof-of-work-chain-which-he-can-get-by-querying-network-nodes-until-hes-convinced-he-has-the-longest-chain--he-cant-check-the-transaction-for-himself-but-by-linking-it-to-a-place-in-the-chain-he-can-see-that-a-network-node-has-accepted-it-and-blocks-added-after-it-further-confirm-the-network-has-accepted-it&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A user only needs to keep a copy of the block headers of the longest proof-of-work chain, which he can get by querying network nodes until he’s convinced he has the longest chain […]. He can’t check the transaction for himself, but by linking it to a place in the chain, he can see that a network node has accepted it, and blocks added after it further confirm the network has accepted it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the blockchain network can now consist of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nodes which have the entirety of the blockchain, with every single transaction detail saved,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nodes which contain some amount of detail (keeping only the relevant transactions using the concept of Merkle Trees), and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Light” nodes, which only keep a copy of the block headers, without any of the details about the transactions which any of the blocks contain. They can however ask (“&lt;em&gt;query&lt;/em&gt;”) other (more “knowledgeable”) nodes on the system if a certain transaction Tx has occurred.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;9-combining-and-splitting-value&quot;&gt;9. Combining and Splitting Value&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not going to lie, I was happy to encounter this chapter. Because up until now, I have only been talking about moving one entire bitcoin from Ann to Bob and then moving that exact same bitcoin from Bob to Charlie. In reality, it is more likely that Bob will receive 1.28523 BTC from Ann, and that he will then have to send 0.762304 BTC to Charlie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section shows that one transaction Tx can contain many inputs and will usually contain two outputs: the first output will be the receiver of the transaction, and the second output will be change (if any) sent back to the sender. Let’s look at an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ann has 0.5 BTC, and wants to send Bob 0.3 BTC. This transaction will break up Ann’s currency into two separate outputs: The 0.3 BTC owed to Bob, and the 0.2 BTC left behind. This 0.2 BTC will be sent back to Ann. Hence why there are two outputs most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we have the concept of “Unspent Transaction Output”, or UTXO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A UTXO is essentially the unused part of a transaction. Every time a cryptocurrency transaction takes place, existing inputs are deleted and new outputs are created. Any outputs that aren’t immediately spent become a UTXO that’s tied to the sender in the transaction.”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.bybit.com/glossary/definition-utxo/&quot;&gt;(source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, the details (with the public/private keys, how to check who has access to what, etc.) are kind of complicated, but even Satoshi doesn’t get into it in the whitepaper so I won’t either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;10-privacy&quot;&gt;10. Privacy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Satoshi talks about pseudonymity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-public-can-see-that-someone-is-sending-an-amount-to-someone-else-but-without-information-linking-the-transaction-to-anyone&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The public can see that someone is sending an amount to someone else, but without information linking the transaction to anyone.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your identity is separate from your bitcoin wallet (mostly not the case today)&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;11-calculations&quot;&gt;11. Calculations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Satoshi simulates an attack on the Bitcoin network. He considers the case where the attacker has less than 50% of the CPU power of the network, and proves that the attacker will have a very (extremely) hard time trying to hack the network; the attacker basically has to be extremely lucky with finding the nonces (as explained in section 4) and creating a separate chain of blocks from the legitimate chain, and adding the blocks onto that chain faster than the legitimate chain is growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, maybe this part isn’t so clear, so let me dive deeper into an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attack-on-the-blockchain-example&quot;&gt;Attack on the Blockchain example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say I pay for a Lamborghini with bitcoin. The dealership tells me “hold on, we want to wait a bit to make sure this transaction is valid, is accepted by everyone and exists on the blockchain”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a fair argument, we wait an hour, they’re convinced, I get my Lambo and head home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I didn’t actually want to pay for the Lambo. In order to break the Bitcoin system, and get my money back (and disappear the Lambo), I have to go back to the block BEFORE the one which contains my lambo purchase, and start a new chain from that point on. The first block that I will add to my “local” blockchain will be exactly the same as the block which contained my transaction with the dealership, except I will remove that transaction. Basically, in my version of reality, this transaction never occurred, i.e. I never paid the dealership anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\btc\img6.png&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, now that I changed something in the block, the hash will likely not start with the required number of 0’s (section 4 topic). So I broke the nonce/data combination by changing the data, and so now I need to “mine” the block and find a new nonce which will yield a block hash starting with the required number of 0’s. Furthermore, by changing one block, I now invalidated every block which followed it, because they all depend on past blocks’ hashes. Now all of their hashes don’t start with the required number of 0’s, and so I will have to “re-mine” all of them and try to catch up with the legitimate blockchain (it’s me against all the honest nodes of the world, and they have a head start). I basically have to get super lucky to find the right nonces for every block, until my chain is longer than the legitimate chain, at which point I announce to other nodes that I have a chain with more “proof-of-work” (i.e. it is longer than everyone else’s), and the nodes on the network will accept my chain as the legitimate one and start to build on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I succeed, the dealership will see tomorrow that they do not have access to the funds which I paid them. They panick, go online to check the blockchain history to verify their transaction with me, and see that it was never recorded and basically never existed… even though yesterday they saw that it was on there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, this will not be happening. The chances are extremely low and the safety of the network grows exponentially as a function of the number of blocks ahead of the block which an attacker wants to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\btc\img7.png&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the snapshot above, &lt;strong&gt;q&lt;/strong&gt; is the percentage of hash power which the attacker has compared to the rest of the system. So in this example, the attaker has 10% of all the hash power. &lt;strong&gt;z&lt;/strong&gt; is the number of blocks in front of the block being attacked. So if there are no blocks in front of the block being attacked, i.e. there is no node in the system that has confirmed what is in the block, well then the probability of attacking it is 100% (the attacker’s created block is as valid as the parallel block which is legitimate, but which also doesn’t have any node confirm it yet). This is why you should do what the lambo dealership did, and wait for the network nodes to confirm the transaction to cement it in the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, things start to turn for the worse once the legitimate block gets another block on top of it (z = 1), i.e. the network have confirmed it and built on top of it. Now the attacker has a 20% chance of catching up. So on and so forth with the other numbers. And from my understanding, the industry standard is to wait for 6 blocks (that’s 1 hour of waiting) in order to be confident that the transaction in question is permanent and will not be reversed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example below this one in the whitepaper shows that if the attacker has 30% of the cpu power, then his chances are much better (5 blocks deep, the attacker has 17% of a successful attack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, all of this goes out the window if the attacker somehow manages to control at least 51% of the network’s computing power. In which case Bitcoin becomes pointless and worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;12-conclusion&quot;&gt;12. Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;nodes-can-leave-and-rejoin-the-network-at-will-accepting-the-proof-of-work-chain-as-proof-of-what-happened-while-they-were-gone-they-vote-with-their-cpu-power-expressing-their-acceptance-of-valid-blocks-by-working-on-extending-them-and-rejecting-invalid-blocks-by-refusing-to-work-on-them-any-needed-rules-and-incentives-can-be-enforced-with-this-consensus-mechanism&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Nodes can leave and rejoin the network at will, accepting the proof-of-work chain as proof of what happened while they were gone. They vote with their CPU power, expressing their acceptance of valid blocks by working on extending them and rejecting invalid blocks by refusing to work on them. Any needed rules and incentives can be enforced with this consensus mechanism.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks to me like a beautiful design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, CPU power has largely followed Moore’s law, which predicts that the number of transistors on a microchip doubles approximately every two years, resulting in a significant increase in processing power.
Processing power has historically followed Moore’s law, which says that the number of transistors on a microchip doubles approximately every two years, resulting in a significant increase in processing power. Although it is unlikely that the trend will continue for long (due to physical limitations), the idea is that processor speed is always increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if 10 years ago the network required you to find a hash with five 0’s, with today’s computational power, five 0’s is a joke. The number of 0’s keeps increasing to keep it difficult to find the winning hash. In fact, the system is set up so that the number of leading 0’s is equivalent to whatever will make someone find the right nonce in about 10 minutes. So it depends on the “hash rate” of the network. If a block was generated in 8 minutes one time, then the next block will increase in difficulty. The more miners there are, the more 0’s there will be, and so the harder it gets. Same thing for faster CPU power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we know if a block is valid? In other words, how do we know that every transaction Tx in the block have not already been put in some block before? Because if transaction Tx has already happened before, then having it occur again would mean we’re “double-spending”, and we don’t want that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to solve this, we must know that every transaction has its own unique ID. The transaction’s ID contains the ID of the block that it’s in, and the transaction number within that block (so is it Tx #1, 2, 50, etc). What we can do is search every block in the block chain that came before to see if this particular transaction can be found somewhere. If not, then this transaction is an original and we can move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In computer science, this is called an O(n) computation. The concept is hard to explain, but basically, we have to check every single block, and that is not the most efficient way of doing it. Instead, we can reduce this to O(log(n)) using the following method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a node, whenever you add a block to the chain, you had to have validate each transaction within that block. And so when you go through them, you can store them inside your RAM (for example). In your database, you can store the transaction IDs in ascending order. And no you have a sorted list of past transactions, and you have a new transaction which you want to check if it is in that list. So now you can run your favorite search algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, we did what’s known as “linear search”, which is searching through every item. But now that we have a sorted list, we can do what’s called a “binary search”. In binary search, the list is divided in half at each step and the search continues in the half that may contain the desired item. This reduces the number of elements to search by half at each step, making this approach much faster than “linear search”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper was written in 2008. Back then, it was simpler to jump in and participate in the network through mining bitcoin. At the time, mining was relatively easy and required only a small amount of computing power.
Regulated exchanges such as Coinbase and Binance didn’t exist back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to fund our Bitcoin wallets today, we must send our  money from our bank to the exchange, and then through the exchange we can put money in our digital wallet. Gone are the days where you could just join the Bitcoin network with a latptop, and earn bitcoin. So this section is a bit obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html">This is the fourth article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bitcoin Part 1.0: Reading the Whitepaper</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin Part 1.0: Reading the Whitepaper" /><published>2023-04-12T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2023-04-12T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-is-the-third-article-in-a-series-where-my-goal-is-to-understand-the-blockchain-nfts-and-the-related-technologies&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the third article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will use the pronouns “he/him” to represent Satoshi Nakamoto, not because I am assuming his/her/their gender, but because it will make things simpler. I would also note that although Satoshi uses “we” all throughout the paper, notably in science and math, it’s quite common for academic papers to say “we” even though it was written by just one author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper&quot;&gt;Reading the Bitcoin whitepaper&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the right and honest way to introduce Bitcoin is by going back to the paper that started it all: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf&quot;&gt;Bitcoin whitepaper&lt;/a&gt;. Now that we have the prerequisites covered, we can dive into this paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the introduction to the Bitcoin whitepaper, Satoshi Nakamoto describes the problem of having to trust intermediaries in financial transactions. He also says says how a centralized authority must settle/mediate disputes, and the more transactions there are, the more disputes there will be, and therefore the higher the operating costs will be. These middlemen are obviously not doing charity work and working for free, so if operating cost goes up, well then they must carry the extra cost onto their users via extra fees, or they will (as Satoshi writes) increase the minimum transaction amount. Then he describes the problem of reversible transactions, where a fraudulent buyer could initiate a transaction, receive the goods, and then initiate a refund to get the money back, leaving the seller without the goods or the payment &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-peer-to-peer-distributed-timestamp-server-to-generate-computational-proof-of-the-chronological-order-of-transactions-the-system-is-secure-as-long-as-honest-nodes-collectively-control-more-cpu-power-than-any-cooperating-group-of-attacker-nodes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“a peer-to-peer distributed timestamp server to generate computational proof of the chronological order of transactions. The system is secure as long as honest nodes collectively control more CPU power than any cooperating group of attacker nodes”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\Server-based-network-vs-Peer-to-Peer-network-Digital-Impact-Labs-2017.png&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea to remember here is that there is no central authority maintaining the system. It’s a system by the users, for the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And regarding the merchant/buyer situation, he writes &lt;em&gt;“Transactions that are computationally impractical to reverse would protect sellers from fraud, and routine escrow mechanisms could easily be implemented to protect buyers”&lt;/em&gt;. I doubt he mentions anything more about setting up these “routine escrow mechanisms”, but let’s read on. The point here is that once something is on the blokchain, it’s permanent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-transactions&quot;&gt;2. Transactions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how will transactions work on this network?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;we-define-an-electronic-coin-as-a-chain-of-digital-signatures&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We define an electronic coin as a chain of digital signatures.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave an introduction to digital signatures in the previous article, but for the whole story on that, check note &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But briefly, if I “digitally sign” something, that’s a proof that I own the private key, which no one else is going to have. So everyone in the world can see a message that has my digital signature and be able to confirm that I signed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;each-owner-transfers-the-coin-to-the-next-by-digitally-signing-a-hash-of-the-previous-transaction-and-the-public-key-of-the-next-owner-and-adding-these-to-the-end-of-the-coin&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Each owner transfers the coin to the next by digitally signing a hash of the previous transaction and the public key of the next owner and adding these to the end of the coin.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that when a bitcoin transaction takes place, the current owner of the bitcoin (i.e. the person who holds the private key to access it) digitally signs a hash of the previous transaction and the public key of the next owner. This digital signature serves as proof that the current owner is indeed authorized to transfer ownership of the coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\btc\img1.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see here, a transaction is nothing more than 3 numbers: the new owners public key, the hash of the previous block, and the old owners signature. As an example, let’s follow the path of 1 bitcoin as Ann first sends it to Bob, and then Bob sends that bitcoin to Charlie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ann wants to send Bob a bitcoin, so within the transaction data she will include Bob’s public key (some number), the hash of the previous transaction (let’s assume we have that) (also some number), and then she will concatenate Bob’s public key with the hash, and encrypt that using her private key, thus signing it. Now that bitcoin belongs to Bob.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Bob wants to send the bitcoin to Charlie. So Bob gets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charlie’s public key, then he takes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the hash of the previous number (basically concatenating the 3 numbers from the “Ann-&amp;gt;Bob” transaction, and taking its hash), and finally&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bob signs the transaction. So now we have the “Bob-&amp;gt;Charlie” transaction pointing back to the “Ann-&amp;gt;Bob” transaction via the hash. On top of that, the the fact that Bob signed this transaction with his private key can be decrypted with his public key, which can be found by going to the previous transaction (the “Ann-&amp;gt;Bob” transaction).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we get a “chain of digital signatures” from all the owners of the coin(s) being transferred (one new owner at a time). And this chain of owners is permanent, so if a hack or illegal activity has occurred and some of that Bitcoin ends up in your possession, law enforcement may be able to trace the transactions and seize the Bitcoin as part of their investigation &lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, there is nothing revolutionary. Using digital signature is old news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-problem-of-course-is-the-payee-cant-verify-that-one-of-the-owners-did-not-double-spend-the-coin-a-common-solution-is-to-introduce-a-trusted-central-authority-or-mint-that-checks-every-transaction-for-double-spending&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The problem of course is the payee can’t verify that one of the owners did not double-spend the coin. A common solution is to introduce a trusted central authority, or mint, that checks every transaction for double spending.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something we want to obviously avoid. And the fact that Bitcoin solved this problem is one of the many reasons why it is so revolutionary &lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;(4)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know your thoughts on this double-spending problem, but I was a bit confused at first. How hard can it be to keep track of who owns what? Why not just give me my private key (my wallet), and have a pointer pointing from my wallet to the Bitcoin that I own. We learn the concept of pointers early on in our C/C++ class. What’s the problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the problem is that I’m still thinking inside the box. This approach would require a trusted central authority to maintain a database of all Bitcoin ownership records, and this would defeat the purpose of Bitcoin’s decentralized and trustless nature. The truth is that hindsight is 20/20; the blockchain’s concept may seem obvious now, but in reality it is revolutionary. Let’s read on to see Satoshi’s solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-only-way-to-confirm-the-absence-of-a-transaction-is-to-be-aware-of-all-transactions-in-the-mint-based-model-the-mint-was-aware-of-all-transactions-and-decided-which-arrived-first-to-accomplish-this-without-a-trusted-party-transactions-must-be-publicly-announced-and-we-need-a-system-for-participants-to-agree-on-a-single-history-of-the-order-in-which-they-were-received-the-payee-needs-proof-that-at-the-time-of-each-transaction-the-majority-of-nodes-agreed-it-was-the-first-received-&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The only way to confirm the absence of a transaction is to be aware of all transactions. In the mint based model, the mint was aware of all transactions and decided which arrived first. To accomplish this without a trusted party, transactions must be publicly announced, and we need a system for participants to agree on a single history of the order in which they were received. The payee needs proof that at the time of each transaction, the majority of nodes agreed it was the first received. “&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An agreed upon chronological order of all transactions is the solution to the double-spending problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-timestamp-server&quot;&gt;3. Timestamp server&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the root of the solution to this problem has already been written in 1991.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this short section, Satoshi talks about data being “timestamped” and somehow publishing it somewhere so that everyone can have access to it (as a generic example, he writes “&lt;em&gt;newspaper&lt;/em&gt;”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, “timestamping” is not a new concept. In 1991, Stuart Haber &amp;amp; Scott Stornetta &lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;(5)&lt;/a&gt; published a paper called &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/bf00196791&quot;&gt;“How to time-stamp a digital document”&lt;/a&gt;. Here are the first two sentences of that paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The prospect of a world in which all text, audio, picture, and video documents are in digital form on easily modifiable media raises the issue of how to certify when a document was created or last changed. The problem is to time-stamp the data, not the medium.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So by now you may be wondering: what is timestamping?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll answer that question by answering what Stuart Haber and Scott Stornetta were trying to answer back in 1991: “how do we create immutable record?”, in other words, “how do we create digital records (of anything) that intrinsically can prove to anyone that they are in fact the original records (that they haven’t been altered)?” And remember, all this without the help of an central authority to tell us “trust me”. Because, digitally, it is easy to copy, alter, and paste. It’s like asking, how do I know for sure that I have the original Mona Lisa that Leonardo da Vinci himself painted? I’ll leave some notes about how to came to think about it &lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;(6)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve this, what they did was literally “time-stamp” data: they combined the time (which is universally agreed upon and it is also a one-way street, i.e. always moving forward and changing) with a particular piece of content, to create something new, that is unique and condesed that into a (unique) hash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In section “7. Application” of their paper, they write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“[…] timestamp a log of documents rather than each document individually. For example, each corporate document created in a day could be hashed, and the hash value added to the company’s daily log of documents. Then, at the end of the business day, the log alone could be submitted for time-stamping. This would eliminate the expense of time-stamping each document individually, while still making it possible to detect tampering with each document; we could also determine whether any documents had been destroyed altogether.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Satoshi also writes the following in this section:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;each-timestamp-includes-the-previous-timestamp-in-its-hash-forming-a-chain-with-each-additional-timestamp-reinforcing-the-ones-before-it&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Each timestamp includes the previous timestamp in its hash, forming a chain, with each additional timestamp reinforcing the ones before it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\btc\img2.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look closer at what this diagram is saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take 3 items which, for whatever reason, we need to prove that they were created at a particular date/time. Let’s now group these items together and call that a “block”. We will now take the hash of the previous block (don’t forget that all “items” are just bits in a computer, so you can take a hash of anything digital) and concatenate the items of the current block, and take the hash of all that. That will be summarized in the “hash” box. Then you simply repeat, and form a chain of blocks and hashes. So let’s say we collect all the logs of a business throughout the day, and at the end of the day, we combine them into a block, take yesterday’s hash, and append it to today’s items, and then calculate the hash of all that. Everyday we will do the same thing, and so if today is Friday, and someone tries to go back and change even one bit from file from Monday’s logs, then this will change the hash value of that block, and affect every hash which was calculated on the following days, since they all depend on Monday’s hash. It is thanks to the link between a hash and every following hash, causing a ripple effect and making it clear that someone changed something from Monday’s documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to remove the centralized authority which takes care of storing this chain of hashes (TSS: “Time-Stamping Server”), Stuart Haber and Scott Stornetta write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[…] several members of the client pool must time-stamp the hash. The members are chosen by means of a pseudorandom generator that uses the hash of the document itself as seed. This makes it infeasible to choose deliberately which clients should and should not time-stamp a given hash. The second method could be implemented without the need for a centralized TSS at all.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what they left Satoshi with, so it is up to him to put a practical implementation to all this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, it’s interesting that Satoshi is so adamant about the fact that the buyer can screw the seller over, and that reversibility of transactions is terrible. We can easily argue against this and say that someone can accidentally send Bitcoin to the wrong address, and would need to reverse the transaction. Or if I purchase a product or service, send the money, but the product or service does not meet my expectations, in which case I’d get screwed over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second article of the series I explained how a digital signature can be made using your private key… sort of. To be honest, I didn’t tell the whole story. I just said how you can use your private key to sign a message by encrypting that message, and anyone with your public key can unencrypt the message to see that you encrypted it, proving that it went through you. Read on to learn how signing actually happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assymetric encryption has its pros and cons. One big “con” is that is that it’s a slow process, compared to its “symmetric counterpart (which we didn’t discuss about, but it doesn’t matter); the mathematical algorithms are more computationally complex and the keys themselves are also more lengthy. Given these two facts, encrypting an entire message is costly. If only there was a way to instead work with a smaller representation of the data (like a fingerprint of the message), then we’d be able to encrypt that instead. Well, there is a way to convert any amount of data into a fixed, relatively small representation of that data, and it’s called hashing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ann writes a message. She then runs her message through a hashing algorithm (SHA256 in the case of Bitcoin). The result will be some 256-bit (64 hexadecimal characters, which is what I showed in the previous article) called a hash, or digest. Now Ann is going to encrypt (with her private key) that message digest, and the result of that will be the encrypted digest. This encrypted digest is the signature for this particular message; it will be appended to the message and sent off to Bob. So now Bob will use Ann’s public key to verify the signature. More specifically, Bob will unencrypt the encrypted message digest, and the result will be the message digest. Then he will independently generate the hash of the message itself, and if his calculated hash is the same as the hash which he unencrypted from Ann, then he knows two things: the message has not been tampered with since it has been signed by Ann (known as “integrity”), and Ann was the one to sign the message (property of “authentication”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to see how a digital signature isn’t like a signature we write by hand. A signature by hand is going to be the same (or at least very similar) every time, while a digital signature will change every time, as long as the messages are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course they would have to follow proper legal procedures and obtain a warrant or court order to seize any assets, including Bitcoin. And if you acquired the Bitcoin through legitimate means and were not aware of any illegal activity, you may have legal options to contest the seizure. That being said, if you went into some underground marketplace to acquire these Bitcoins at a price lower than the market price, well then you were likely in the receiving end of Bitcoin “dumping”, i.e. those Bitcoins were likely acquired illegally and the person is just trying to get rid of them quickly. That’s why it’s always best to buy and sell Bitcoin through legitimate, regulated exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other reasons why it’s revolutionary are: decentralization (maintained by a global community of users), transparency (anyone with an internet connection can access it and inspect it), immutability (this is important if you want to be trustworthy), limited supply (different from any other currency like fiat currency or commodity like gold), and it is programmable (open-source software that can be used for other more complex applications requiring blockchain tech).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question these two were trying to solve was “how do we create immutable record?”, in other words, “how do we create digital records (of anything) that intrinsically can prove to anyone that they are the original records (that they haven’t been altered)?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, they thought that this problem had no solution. As they were writing their proof that you cannot remove the need to trust someone, they ended up seeing that this proof can be looked at in the other direction, and could be made to work. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WWVoPBkPd6g&quot;&gt;In Scott Stornetta’s words&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;if two people are trying to prove something, but they collude, then you need a third person to look over their shoulder. But what if they draw that (third) person in the collusion, well then you need a fourth person, and so on and so forth. As a result, we were trying to prove the absurdity of the act that you had to eventually trust someone. Phrashing it that way, I realized that the collusion would have to involve everyone in the world. And then I realized if you turn that upside down and created a system of interlinked documents with essentially everyone as a witness, then you had in fact solved the problem.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html">This is the third article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bitcoin Part 0: Technical Prerequisites</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper-(Part-1)/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bitcoin Part 0: Technical Prerequisites" /><published>2023-04-07T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper-(Part-1)</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Reading-the-bitcoin-whitepaper-(Part-1)/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-is-the-second-article-in-a-series-where-my-goal-is-to-understand-the-blockchain-nfts-and-the-related-technologies&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the second article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encryption-and-digital-signatures&quot;&gt;Encryption and digital signatures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of cryptography, there is something called “public key cryptography”, a.k.a. “asymmetric cryptography”. Since this is used in the blockchain, let’s go over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you open a Bitcoin wallet, you are given a private key. This “private key” is what you will use to prove to others that you are who you say you are. It is private, and only you should have it. Once the private key is generated, a public key is derived from it mathematically (using Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm, or ECDSA). This one is public, and so everyone can have access to it. Any message encrypted with the private key can only be decrypted with the corresponding public key, and, similarly, any message encrypted with the public key can only be decrypted with the corresponding private key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pair of keys can make two things happen (depending on which one is used to encrypt):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s say Ann wants to send Bob a secret message. Ann wants only Bob to be able to read it. To do that, she will take Bob’s publicly available public key, and encrypt her messsage. The message is now encrypted. The only way to unencrypt the message, is to use the private key associated with the public key used to encrypt the message; Ann used Bob’s public key to encrypt the messsage, and so only Bob’s private key can be used to decrypt the message. Luckily, only Bob has access to his private key, which means that only Bob can decrypt and read the secret message. In cybersecurity, this is called “data confidentiality”; this is the idea that the data is only accessible to the intended recipient.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s say Ann wants to send Bob a message, but the message isn’t secret. In other words, she doesn’t care if her message gets intercepted and read by someone else. Confidentiality is not of a concern to her. However, Ann wants to prove that she wrote the message. She wants to add her “signature” on the message. So what Ann will do is write the message, encrypt it with her private key, send it to Bob, and if Bob can successfully decrypt the message using Ann’s public key, that proves that Ann was the sender of the message. This is what is known as “authentication”. The only key that could’ve encrypted the message was Ann’s private key, which is only in Ann’s possession. On top of “authentication”, this also proves “data integrity”, i.e. the message has not been tampered with while in transit. Why is that the case? Because if someone were to capture Ann’s message and change its content content (since everyone has access to her public key), when Bob will try to decrypt the message with Ann’s public key, it would result in gibberish. If Bob is successfully able to decrypt the message with Ann’s public key, this proves that the message was encrypted using Ann’s private key, and only Ann has access to it. Effectively, Ann signed her message, thus providing both authentication and integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, you can’t just say “Hey, this is Bob, and I am sending Ann 5 BTC” because anyone could make that claim. Instead, you use your private key to generate a digital signature that proves that you are the legitimate owner of the funds being sent, and that you authorized the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, the reason why this “public key cryptography” method works is due to the fact that the public/private key pair creation is a one-way street: it is easy to generate a public key from a private key, but it is practically impossible to generate the private key from the public key&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;. Effectively, no one can pretend that they are Ann. The day that computers will be able to derive the private key from the public key, Bitcoin (and all secure communication protocols), will become insecure and be worthless &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hashing&quot;&gt;Hashing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bitcoin blockchain uses a hashing algorithm called SHA-256 (SHA stands for Secure Hash Algorithm).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SHA-256 is used mainly during the mining step (the Proof of Work algorithm).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hashing is the process of converting data of any size (could be the number “0”, could be all of Shakespeare’s writings combined) into a fixed-size string of characters, which is a unique representation of that data. For example, inputting “hello” into the SHA-256 hashing function gives us ‘2cf24dba5fb0a30e26e83b2ac5b9e29e1b161e5c1fa7425e73043362938b9824’.
Changing the input by just a bit changes the hashing output (a.k.a the “hash” or “message digest”) completely: inputting “helo” into the SHA-256 hashing function gives us ‘f4e454f802b88d2f64168ff1742e8cf413fd677d38b87cbefb45821f8981b912’. Completely different output, and no two inputs will have the same output (theoretically).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll get into the details of how hashing is used in the next article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-double-spending-problem&quot;&gt;The double-spending problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you put your house on the market, and a bunch of buyers come in to take a look, what stops you from telling Buyer A that you are selling him the house, and the next day telling Buyer B that you are selling her a house? So I would get the money from both Buyers, disappear, and let them deal with the mess. Well, I can’t do that because when I sell the house to Buyer A, even though I’m not physically giving the house to him, the government keeps records of the ownership transfer. Every home purchase/sale is backed by records in a database which is ran by some government agency (the provincial land registry office).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example, the government (as well as mortgage lenders, attorneys, brokers) act as middlemen in order to ensure that the land/property transfer goes smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if there was no middlemen? Well, then, maybe I would be able to lie to Buyer A and B, and get double the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Bitcoin, there is no trusted third-party to oversee transactions. For that simple reason, the double-spending problem exists. And this problem had no solution, until the Bitcoin whitepaper was published!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the blockchain works through a concesus mechanism where the majority of miners legitimize a transaction as valid. If you want to double-spend your bitcoin, you’ll have to convince at least 51% of the miners in the world to jump on board with your plan (or you have to control 51% of the mining power).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is no minute task. Because with a well-established blockchain like the bitcoin blockchain, which has been around for years and spans all around the world, this type of attack is extremely unlikely to occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Some final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin provides secure, transparent, and immutable record-keeping, all without the need for centralized intermediaries. But it doesn’t come without its (relatively small) negatives (more like inconveniences). Consider other aspects of our lives. For example, when you buy a home, a real estate agent tags along for the ride with you, acting as a middleman between you and the seller. But can you look for homes and figure things out on your own? Sure you can, there’s no need for a middleman. But there are pros and cons to both methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real estate agents have access to a wealth of knowledge and resources, including comprehensive databases of properties for sale, experience with negotiating deals, and knowledge of the local market (hopefully all, but you have to trust them). They can provide valuable guidance throughout the home-buying process and help you avoid costly mistakes. However, their services come at a cost (in the form of a commission fee).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Bitcoin’s decentralized and trustless system offers many benefits, such as increased transparency, security, and reduced fees. However, it also requires a certain level of technical knowledge and responsibility on the part of the user to ensure the safety and security of their funds. It’s definitely not for my grandmother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only are quantum computers needed to break ECDSA, but the ones we have today are very far from being able to break this cryptographic algorithm. It is estimated that a quantum computer of around 2000-4000 high-quality qubits would be necessary to break Bitcoin’s cryptography. Today’s most powerful quantum computer operates at 433 qubits (IBM’s Osprey). However, it’s important to note that the number of qubits alone is not necessarily the only factor in determining a quantum computer’s overall computational power (hencce why I previously wrote “high-quality” qubits).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I would like to mention that while quantum computers are developing, so too are the encryption techniques. If quantum computers will one day be able to break today’s cryptography, then maybe they can be used to retrieve the coins of those wallets that are lost or forgotten, and all active wallets can be upgraded in their encryption, as to not be vulnerable to quantum computers. It can be like mining Bitcoin in the years after 2140, when there will be no more new Bitcoin to mine, and so companies can develop quantum computers with one incentive being the mining of “lost” Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve once heard said, “when Satoshi’s coins move, we will know that quantum computers have become powerful enough to compromise the security of Bitcoin”, or something along those lines.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html">This is the second article in a series where my goal is to understand the blockchain, NFTS, and the related technologies.</summary></entry></feed>