<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-29T18:01:38-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andrei Guevorkian</title><subtitle>Personal Portfolio and Blog.</subtitle><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Problems With Fast Food</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/the-problems-with-fast-foods/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Problems With Fast Food" /><published>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/the-problems-with-fast-foods</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/the-problems-with-fast-foods/">&lt;p&gt;Things found in their natural form are usually better than the ones we’ve messed with. Foods which are scientifically engineered to get us hooked are everywhere (love this short video stating how foods cooked by corporations are different than foods cooked at home). In the most extreme of cases, take heroine, which comes from poppy seeds, cocaine from the coca plant &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;, and alcohol from grains or fruits. We are now capable of refining and concentrating harmless plants so much that it can make people lose complete control of themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We love our fried chicken, our french fries, our samosas, our pizza puffs, our hashbrowns, our deep-fried calamari, our doughnuts etc. Our prehistoric minds love foods high in fat, as they provide the biggest bang for your buck in terms of energy (at 9 calories per gram, versus carbs and proteins which 
contain only 4). &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fat in itself is definitely not bad. There is nothing bad with any of the three macro-nutrients. We need all three of them. What is more likely to cause the terrible health problems we see today are processed foods. The more processed something is, the worst it’ll be for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s so bad about fried food other than the extra calories it brings? Let’s look at the chemistry behind frying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the naked eye, the process of frying involves placing a breaded chicken, for example, onto a pan of oil, where the hot oil intensely bubbles until one lowers the heat and decides that the chicken is brown and crispy enough. Here are the behind-the-scenes frying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recipes require the oil to be heated to temperatures around 350 degrees Fahrenheit (178 degrees Celsius). You can verify this by dropping placing your breaded chicken onto the oil, and it starts bubbling. That bubbling is not the oil boiling, but rather the moister boiling off from the surface of the food &lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;. With the loss of moisture comes not only the formation of a crispy crust, but also space for the food to absorb the oil it’s being cooked in. This increases the calorie count (on top of the batter/flour typically used during frying).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: Coca-Cola is a combination of two words: “coca” (the same coca leaf used to make cocaine, because yes, in fact, they did use cocaine before 1903, when there was pressure to remove it due to racism (read)), and “cola” or today known as “kola”, i.e. the kola nut from which caffeine is made. Due to its illegality, cocaine is removed, and replaced with the legal but lethal sugar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love evolutionary arguments, so here’s one: back in our hunter-gatherer days, we would need foods high in calories to give us energy to hunt. Fat happens to have 9 calories per gram, while carbs and proteins have 4. So fatty foods were good for us, but carbohydrates were also good for us because it is the quickest form of energy we can have (broken down into “glucose”). For foods high in carbs, think of sweet foods, and back in the hunter-gatherer days, these were mainly fruits and honey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how these foods are “sweet”, which is a “good” taste. This is so because our taste buds have evolved to like these foods and to associate them to a pleasurable experience, because evolutionarily, these were the foods to provide us with a lot of energy. It is in our body’s best interest to signal to the brain which foods are good (sweet and calorie-dense) and which are bad (like a toxic berry, which could have been “sour”, and hence why we don’t like sour food).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is by no coincidence today that most foods sold to us are high in carbs and fats. Corporations are taking advantage of our evolutionary. The industrial and technological revolution hit us fast, and our brains did not have the time to evolve with the environment. Our sedentary lifestyles do not require us to eat as much (since we move less on average), and so we end up storing all the extra carbs as glycogen in the liver. Once the liver is full, that glycogen is stored as fat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all carbs are bad. “Complex carbs” are those which raise the blood sugar level slowly and leaves you feeling “full” for longer (think multigrain bread, brown rice, lentils, beans). “Simple carbs” are the bad ones which raise blood sugar levels quickly and don’t satisfy hunger for too long (think candy, fruit juice, honey). That is why it is recommended to eat “quickly digested carbs” when you have low blood sugar levels, (because they get the job done fast).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oils typically boil at almost twice the boiling temperature of water. See this chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wTNlHyjip94&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wTNlHyjip94&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5S6-v37nOtY&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5S6-v37nOtY&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wa.kaiserpermanente.org/healthAndWellness?item=%2Fcommon%2FhealthAndWellness%2Fconditions%2Fdiabetes%2FfoodBalancing.html&quot;&gt;https://wa.kaiserpermanente.org/healthAndWellness?item=%2Fcommon%2FhealthAndWellness%2Fconditions%2Fdiabetes%2FfoodBalancing.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://healthguides.healthgrades.com/take-charge-of-your-diabetes-treatment/what-to-eat-when-you-have-low-blood-sugar&quot;&gt;https://healthguides.healthgrades.com/take-charge-of-your-diabetes-treatment/what-to-eat-when-you-have-low-blood-sugar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Science" /><summary type="html">Things found in their natural form are usually better than the ones we’ve messed with. Foods which are scientifically engineered to get us hooked are everywhere (love this short video stating how foods cooked by corporations are different than foods cooked at home). In the most extreme of cases, take heroine, which comes from poppy seeds, cocaine from the coca plant (1), and alcohol from grains or fruits. We are now capable of refining and concentrating harmless plants so much that it can make people lose complete control of themselves.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Planet of the Trees</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/planet-of-the-trees/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planet of the Trees" /><published>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/planet-of-the-trees</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/planet-of-the-trees/">&lt;p&gt;The tallest tree in the world is the redwood tree located in the state of California. They can grow to be over a hundred meters tall. But why are they so tall? And how tall can they grow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees have two main opposing forces pulling them towards each other. First, trees need natural resources from the ground below them (water, nitrogen, phosphorus, etc). The shorter the tree is, the easier it is for those resources to reach the top of the tree. However, trees also need sunlight, and competition can be serious at times between neighboring trees. These trees, for example, found in Anza-Borrego Desert State Park in California have blocked so much sunlight that even if there is enough resources provided by the soil, another tree will not be able to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\tree.png&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get as much sunlight to the leaves as possible, trees have the incentive to grow larger than their neighboring trees. Hence why they grow vertically. And if there is not a lot of competition, then they won’t grow as tall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one can imagine, there is a “Goldilocks Zone” for trees. They can’t just grow too tall, because then the leaves will be too far away from the ground and more energy will be wasted by trying to get the water up to the leaves  than was gained by being closer to the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the redwoods in California, we can say that they got lucky because the conditions they live in are good for their growth: steady/warm climate, nutrient-rich soil, healthy amount of rain, occasional fog (providing the leaves at the top with needed water, rather than having to get all of it from the soil), and of course, competition (it’s a forest down there!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-evolutionary-benefit-for-palm-trees-to-grow-so-tall&quot;&gt;https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-evolutionary-benefit-for-palm-trees-to-grow-so-tall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/14667-tall-trees-grow.html&quot;&gt;https://www.livescience.com/14667-tall-trees-grow.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/Is-there-a-reason-why-trees-grow-so-tall&quot;&gt;https://www.quora.com/Is-there-a-reason-why-trees-grow-so-tall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;photo-credit&quot;&gt;Photo Credit:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-evolutionary-benefit-for-palm-trees-to-grow-so-tall&quot;&gt;https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-evolutionary-benefit-for-palm-trees-to-grow-so-tall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Science" /><summary type="html">The tallest tree in the world is the redwood tree located in the state of California. They can grow to be over a hundred meters tall. But why are they so tall? And how tall can they grow?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Basics of SpaceX</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/basics-of-spacex/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Basics of SpaceX" /><published>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/basics-of-spacex</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/basics-of-spacex/">&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the man behind SpaceX, Elon Musk. In 1995, at the age of 28, he co-founded a software company called Zip2 and sold it for $340M 4 years later. He then founded X.com, a banking website, which then turned into PayPal and was sold to eBay in 2002 for $1.5B. Musk owned 11.7% of PayPal, and so he earned $165M. That same year, with $100M under his belt to be invested in an aerospace company, he created SpaceX (or “Space Exploration Technology”). Musk’s ultimate goal with this it is to make humans an interplanetary species. That doesn’t just mean leaving our footprints on Mars; it means to colonize it. The man has some strong ambitions that’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you haven’t seen the Falcon Heavy, STOP READING and WATCH THIS.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/A0FZIwabctw&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.teslarati.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/Falcon-Heavy-B1052-B1053-LZ-landing-SpaceX-1-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;testhere&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/A0FZIwabctw&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Click here or the image above to be redirected to the Youtube video!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before SpaceX entered the game of rocket development, NASA and other government-funded companies such as Boeing and Lockheed Martin were the only players in the space transport industry for decades. These companies had no incentive in becoming more efficient, and with government funding, they would buy all their engines, hardware and software components from third party companies. As you can imagine, some of these 3rd party companies had their own suppliers. This creates a tree of suppliers, with the complex aerospace companies at the top of it. Each of those suppliers had to make some profit, and so by the time the component reached the top of the tree, i.e. the aerospace companies, all the different components became expensive. On top of that, the aerospace companies had to hire teams and spend time just to figure out and make sure the different components made in different parts of the world by different companies actually work well together. SpaceX however, changed that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SpaceX produces 85% of its components in-house. They are simply going with what makes more economic sense. The problem with the rocket industry is that it’s relatively small, and so there are not too many suppliers for rocket parts. When monopolies exist, that means prices tend to be on the more expensive side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did building components in-house result in lower costs, but it also sped things up a lot. SpaceX engineers were all under the same roof, designing, developing, building, and testing their components from scratch. SpaceX has big ambitions and short deadlines, so they could not afford to wait for the suppliers &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;. With such speedy results, they are able to make money by launching satellites into orbit for private satellite operators. They also deliver cargo to the ISS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SpaceX has contracts with three major types of customers: commercial telecom companies, NASA, and the US military. All have different needs, but the end goal is to get whatever they need up into space. As SpaceX is reusing parts of their rockets, they offer competitive prices for launching, all while making a profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, SpaceX’s main competitor, United Launch Alliance (ULA), which consists of Lockheed Martin and Boeing, charges around $400M for a military satellite launch, while SpaceX charges around $80M (5 times cheaper).
Here is what’s next for SpaceX: the Big Falcon Rocket (BFR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was probably very difficult in the early stages, but with more practice and experience in in-house development, and with more people and more automated systems, things got easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elon_Musk&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elon_Musk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h97fXhDN5qE&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h97fXhDN5qE&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/spacex/comments/24o5pf/what_doesnt_spacex_produce_inhouse&quot;&gt;http://www.reddit.com/r/spacex/comments/24o5pf/what_doesnt_spacex_produce_inhouse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Business" /><summary type="html">Let’s start with the man behind SpaceX, Elon Musk. In 1995, at the age of 28, he co-founded a software company called Zip2 and sold it for $340M 4 years later. He then founded X.com, a banking website, which then turned into PayPal and was sold to eBay in 2002 for $1.5B. Musk owned 11.7% of PayPal, and so he earned $165M. That same year, with $100M under his belt to be invested in an aerospace company, he created SpaceX (or “Space Exploration Technology”). Musk’s ultimate goal with this it is to make humans an interplanetary species. That doesn’t just mean leaving our footprints on Mars; it means to colonize it. The man has some strong ambitions that’s for sure.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A View of the World Through the Lens of Physics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/a-view-of-the-world-throug-the-lens-of-physics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A View of the World Through the Lens of Physics" /><published>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/a-view-of-the-world-throug-the-lens-of-physics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/a-view-of-the-world-throug-the-lens-of-physics/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;here-is-a-relatively-long-article-i-wrote-back-in-my-days-of-college-just-thought-id-share-it-here&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here is a relatively long article I wrote back in my days of college, just thought I’d share it here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are natural learners. From the day we arrive in this world, we are constantly exploring and seeking new patterns. Look at infants, and you will most often see curiosity in their eyes. They all embark on a quest to discover how the things around them work and behave. That is, in essence, the framework of physics. But now the following question arises: how does knowing the basics of physics improve the quality of life of the average person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word physics comes from a Greek word meaning “knowledge of nature.” This knowledge can be spoken in words, but it is most accurately described by mathematical formulas. Mathematics is considered (at least by the scientific community) to be the language of the universe. Any occurrence and any property of any object in the universe should, in principle, be able to be described mathematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a cat might not seem to behave in a mathematical fashion, nor possess any mathematical properties, the most fundamental constituents of that cat do. This is because elementary particles making up regular everyday matter possess mathematical properties. Each particle has an assigned numbers representing, for example, their charge. Looking at things from this basis makes this “math is everywhere” statement seem less crazy. But mathematics on its own is just a bunch of numbers and equations (whether they were invented or discovered is a topic for another time). Physics is what takes advantage of this language to explain the things that happen all around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a better feel for how physics works in everyday life, let’s take an example. If a typical amateur soccer player curves a ball and is then asked how this strange event was produced, he will probably say that he just knows how to do it, but does not know exactly how and why it works. It just does. He can reproduce it again if you want to see it, but that is it. Why would he even need to know exactly how it works? Such useless information. Or is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a thorough examination of the event in a controlled environment (this is where the scientific method comes into play), physicists determine that it is the fluid in which the ball spins that causes a sideways force onto the ball. In physics, a fluid is something that can flow (either a liquid or a gas), and in the case of the kicked soccer ball, the fluid is the surrounding air. Today, the effect that causes this type of curvature is known as the Magnus Effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was very informative, but now what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Magnus Effect was first discovered in the 17th century and occupies an incredibly small place in the field of physics, it is to this day applied effectively in rotor ships (a.k.a. Flettner ships). These ships are equipped with big spinning cylinders which deflect winds in such a manner (based on the Magnus Effect) that they propel themselves forward without the need of any kind of motor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now think about it. A fully loaded ship that travels without the use of fuel? Sounds like a plan, and with all the environmental concerns of today, these ships have gained popularity and are subject to being upgraded using more modern technologies. And all this because while watching a game of tennis, some person named Newton (1642-1726) decided to ask himself, “Why is it that the tennis ball curves when hit in specific ways?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then again, why would the average person, who will never have to apply physics in his day to day life, need to know even the basics of the field? Since at the end of the day, it’s not everyone who is in charge of designing and building that ship that bases its functioning on a law of physics. To hit the point home, let’s say every single person in the world had some basic level of scientific literacy. What would that change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People tend to think that physics is a hard to reach subject that is absent from the everyday world. However, physics is more than just a set of information used by engineers and scientists only. You might think that it’s a way of seeing the world, but it’s even more than that. In fact, it is seeing the world as it really is! Seeing what the universe is made of and how it behaves at its more fundamental level. The beauty of physics is that it doesn’t matter whether we believe in the image that it provides us or not, because it shows us what really is, and it will not change to accommodate anyone’s beliefs about how they would like the universe to behave. Man-made laws such as traffic laws can be broken, but with the laws of physics, we don’t stand a chance! For that reason alone, it makes sense to understand the rules that govern the world we live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this day, different people are preoccupied with different things. Everyone has their own opinions about a wide variety of topics. But those opinions are not always based on facts, and when faced with the truth, opinions don’t matter anymore. Science as a whole is what searches for that truth. But how much science is enough for a person to be considered “scientifically literate.” Basic scientific literacy does not imply learning by heart the exact value of different constants and equations. It rather implies the adoption of the scientific method as a guiding tool to analyze any given situation in life. Knowing just enough to the point where you can analyze some basic data and come up with your own conclusions would be ideal. This could come in handy when confronted with other people’s claims regarding just about anything.  People would start forming logical ideas about different matters and base their opinions on a more concrete basis. Society as a whole would start making more correct decisions. In fact, as Neil deGrasse Tyson, the famous astrophysicist and science communicator, has said,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“you have not fully expressed your power as a voter until you have scientific literacy in topics that matter for future political issues.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Science" /><summary type="html">Here is a relatively long article I wrote back in my days of college, just thought I’d share it here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Operation Ajax (Iran)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/operation-ajax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Operation Ajax (Iran)" /><published>2020-03-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/operation-ajax</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/operation-ajax/">&lt;p&gt;It all started with the 35th Prime Minister of Iran, Mohammad Mosaddegh. This man was loved by the Iranian people and democratically voted to his position in 1951. He made it clear to everyone that he was not fond of the fact that his country’s internal affairs were being influenced and manipulated by foreign actors. Alongside the introduction of numerous social reforms, his main focus was on nationalizing the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (AIOC) &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mosaddegh believed that the UK was ripping them off and stealing their resources. His ideas were supported by everyone, and so Iran’s oil industry quickly became nationalized, meanwhile foreign corporate representatives were sent off from Iran. It was believed that these actions were long overdue, as people have been watching their wealth disappear into the hands of westerners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Mosaddegh’s popularity grew among his own people, the UK was displeased by his actions. They organized a worldwide boycott of Iranian products (3), increased their naval power in the Persian Gulf, and asked the US for help. Then-president, Harry Truman, was not interested, but once Dwight Eisenhower took office in 1953, it was go time. Britain’s argument was that Mosaddegh would easily be influenced by Russia to partner up (the Cold War pretext).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence Operation Ajax was born. It’s goal was to first convince the Shah that Mosaddegh had to be dismissed, and secondly (and most importantly), take back control of the oil fields in Iran. After many negotiations and bribing of the Shah and his family, a planned and fabricated coup was to take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK’s BBC had a branch in Iran, and used that as a main platform to spread propaganda against Mosaddegh. People were hired by the CIA to stage pro-Shah riots and to stir the political situation in Iran. A “communist revolution” was starting to take place as well (prepared of course by the US). Clashes in the streets were more frequent between groups with opposing political opinions. All of this took a major toll on Mosaddegh’s popularity, as people were starting to blame him for the economic and political crisis. He started to use his “emergency powers” to rule, and this was a sign to people that he had become a dictator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing led to another, and in mid-1953, Mosaddegh was officially overthrown. This coup orchestrated entirely by the US and the UK is today a major part of Iranian history. The year that the UK and the US overthrew Iran’s democracy
In 1954, control of Iran’s oil was handed to a total of 8 oil companies, 5 of which were American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This company was able to enter Iran in the first place when, in 1901, a British millionaire negotiated with the then-Shah of Persia (King of Persia) to grant him rights to explore, export, transport and sell petroleum and natural gas in Persia. In return, the Shah received a lot of money and 16% of net profits of the AIOC from their operations. This was called the D’Arcy Concession. And this entire operation was completely backed the the UK government, who, back then (and still to this day) was in a rivalry against Russia. This agreement was a key component of UK’s plan to stop Russia’s influence and have control over an important geographical position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AIOC later became BP (British Petroleum).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blockade put a serious strain on Iran’s economy, and disallowed Mosaddegh to actually keep his promises regarding domestic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1953_Iranian_coup_d%27%C3%A9tat&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1953_Iranian_coup_d%27%C3%A9tat&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad_Mosaddegh&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad_Mosaddegh&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-Persian_Oil_Company&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-Persian_Oil_Company&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H8ybj5KULmA&amp;amp;feature=emb_title&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H8ybj5KULmA&amp;amp;feature=emb_title&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="History" /><summary type="html">It all started with the 35th Prime Minister of Iran, Mohammad Mosaddegh. This man was loved by the Iranian people and democratically voted to his position in 1951. He made it clear to everyone that he was not fond of the fact that his country’s internal affairs were being influenced and manipulated by foreign actors. Alongside the introduction of numerous social reforms, his main focus was on nationalizing the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (AIOC) (1)(2).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tulip Mania</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/Tulip-Mania/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tulip Mania" /><published>2020-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/Tulip-Mania</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/Tulip-Mania/">&lt;p&gt;Here’s the situation. We’re in the 1590’s, in the Dutch Republic, aka the United Provinces (modern day Netherlands). Since the 1550’s, tulips had first been introduced into Europe from Turkey (they grow in many regions in Central Asia, but it became popular in Turkey in the 1500’s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\tulips.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These were some of the most beautiful flowers that the Europeans had ever seen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for 40 years, these beautiful flowers were only possessed by the rich. They would plant them in their gardens to demonstrate their wealth. However, the arrival of these flowers also coincided with The Netherlands’ independence from Spain (which happened in 1582, and which was mainly due to their invention of an early form of capitalism), after which the country prospered economically in a period called the Dutch Golden Age (which roughly spanned the 17th century) &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;. The middle class in the country was growing in size, and the flower naturally became a status symbol (it’s something the rich already possessed, and so if you want to seem rich, now’s your chance). These people were willing to pay a lot just to get their hands on the newest, the latest, and the most spectacular-looking tulips (consumption/materialism basically).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, some dutch (actually Flemish, but same thing) botanist planted a bunch of tulip bulbs (seeds) in his garden, and noticed that these flowers could survive in the harsh conditions of the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These flowers were touched by a disease which would change their color. This caused the petals to display flame-like multicolored stripes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\tulips.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this was a disease, which is NOT a good thing, this introduced even more variety to an already unique-looking flower, and made these flowers more desirable to a population who were unaware of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that tulips are not easy to breed. It takes 10 years for a seed to grow into a flower. As the seed grows, it gives off bulbs which can be collected a few times a year, and which take 3 years instead of 10 to mature. Another characteristic of these flowers is that they blossom during the months of April and May. In that form, the flowers cannot be moved. You would have to wait until summer for them to retrieve into their bulb form. This gives a limited window of time to trade and move the bulbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;..\images\tulippic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;trees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A painting of a “Viceroy”, a type of tulip which, at the peak of the bubble, was worth 10 times more than what a skilled worker made in a year. That’s like it being worth $300’000USD today. For just one.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine this scenario. It’s mid-April, 1634, the sun is shining, and I have a beautiful multi-color and striped tulip in my backyard. I randomly bought it from someone else as a bulb. You, the reader, saw it and wanted to buy it. I want to sell it and make a profit. But the flower is blossomed, and pulling it out of the earth would kill it. So I can’t sell it right away, but what I could do instead, is sign a contract promising that I will sell it to you in the future. In finance, this is a derivative/contract called “futures contract”. These contracts allowed for the tulip bulbs to be traded much more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the story: so you pay me 2000 florins for it (the currency), and I give you a signed futures contract.
But you’re smart (I know it because you got thus far into this article). You know that you can buy this bulb, and sell it for even more to one of your acquaintances. You don’t have the physical bulb yet, but that doesn’t matter, because you know you’ll get it. It says so in the contract which I signed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what you do is you promise your acquaintance of a future sale of the tulip. And maybe he does the same to someone he knows.
Now, people are not buying the flowers to own the actual flowers, but because they just want to make money. Everyone just speculated on the future price of the tulips being higher than the price that they paid for them. Fortunately, at some point, common sense does kick in, and people aren’t willing to pay the crazy amount for a tulip bulb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what happened in February of 1637. Auctions had been ongoing in these times, and tulips had been selling like crazy. But, one day, in one particular tulip auction in a city called Haarlem, no one showed up to buy the tulips &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just like that, overnight, the price of these flowers plummeted, as people desperately tried to sell their flowers. More specifically, as more and more traders were selling, they had to lower their prices to compete with each other. And as the prices go even lower, even more people want to get rid of their bulbs, which then drives prices even lower &lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often considered to be the first ever economic bubble, the “tulip mania” is a basic case and an easy to understand one with not too many variables (contrasted with our more complex world of today). To summarize and possibly clear things up, a bubble occurs when your friend tells you that he bought something, and made a profit by selling it at a higher price. So you do the same as him, and sell it for even more. At this point, everyone hears of the opportunities of making easy money here. Knowing about the actual value of the item does not matter anymore. The trend is just too good to ignore. You buy low, and sell high. Everyone’s been doing it for the past few months or years… until, one day, there are no more buyers. People suddenly realize that they don’t actually want to spend that much money on this object. The price of that item hence crashes. This marks the burst of the bubble. And like all bubbles to date, they must burst at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bubble begins at the point when the item starts selling for more than its intrinsic value. Although it’s hard to pinpoint the real worth of something, it is easier to spot when things get ridiculous. And herein lies the danger of bubbles, we only spot them when it’s too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that all this happened in the 1600’s. There is very limited economic data from that era, and not everything is necessarily true. But that doesn’t matter. The tulip mania teaches us valuable lessons nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands were able to improve their naval power, which gave rise to Dutch East India Company, which is the first known corporation. This led to the first ever stock market to be located in Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A this time, there was a plague outbreak, and this is a possible reason for no one to show up. Some even argue that it was because of this plague outbreak that the tulip mania started, as people thought they were going to die anyway, so didn’t mind paying a lot of money for a flower. YOLO right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something crafty that some sellers tried to do is take a horse to the nearest city, and sell all their now-worthless bulbs over there, before that city found out about the price drop in Haarlem. Within four days, the crash which occurred in Haarlem touched the entire country. High Frequency Traders do something similar today, building their IT location as close as possible to the exchange in order to receive the data faster. Every microsecond counts today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tulip_mania&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tulip_mania&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-livicJXWDk&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-livicJXWDk&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I5ZR0jMlxX0&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I5ZR0jMlxX0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Economics" /><category term="History" /><summary type="html">Here’s the situation. We’re in the 1590’s, in the Dutch Republic, aka the United Provinces (modern day Netherlands). Since the 1550’s, tulips had first been introduced into Europe from Turkey (they grow in many regions in Central Asia, but it became popular in Turkey in the 1500’s).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">John D. Rockefeller</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/John-D.-Rockefeller/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="John D. Rockefeller" /><published>2020-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/John-D.-Rockefeller</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/John-D.-Rockefeller/">&lt;p&gt;John D. Rockefeller was born in 1839 in NYC. His father was of English and German descent and his mother was of Scots-Irish descent. When people speak of the Rockefellers, it’s because of John. John D. Rockefeller not only built an empire, but he did so with humble beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His mother was very religious and disciplined, and had a major influence on John. At church he was encouraged to make as much money as he could, and then give away as much of it as he could. This really resonated with him, and from his first job as an assistant bookkeeper at the age of 16, he would donate a portion of his small earnings to his local church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was very good at what he did. He was very systematic in his approach to everything, and he was very surprised at how slow and inefficient his older bosses were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once he had reached his 20’s, John took a loan of 1000$ from his father, and threw himself into the risky business of commodity trading. He made some more money there, but then, with the oil boom happening, he saw great opportunity in the oil industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in 1859, the oil boom in Pensylvania was under way, and everyone wanted a piece of it. However, by the time John got to Pensylvania, the drilling market was already saturated, and it became a risky business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John would let others go through the hassle of finding the oil and drilling it, and he would just buy it off them to refine it. Refining the oil was something that not a lot of people were doing. That’s where the study money was to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1863, John and some partners opened an oil refinery in Cleveland, and they made sure to be very efficient with it. John’s team of chemists and engineers not only optimized the refining process, but also found numerous useful byproducts which were not yet discovered. In fact, only 60% of the oil refined was put to good use (kerosene), while the other 40% was put to waste. John changed that and started selling the by-products as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockefeller used “monopolistic practices” to force his competitors to bankruptcy. Those who did not give up and fought back, were subject to Rockefeller’s “price wars”. This consisted of dropping their (Rockefeller’s) price of oil so cheap (to as much as 80% of its original value!), that even he would not make a profit. However, he was in a position where he could hold this negative balance sheet much longer than his competitors, and so he would outlast them to their bankruptcy. Thus, John had bought the majority of all his competitors’ refineries (from 26 companies in the region down to 4). The heads of those 4 resisting companies were later invited to join the company, and hence combining the brightest minds in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1870, John formed Standard Oil of Ohio to replace his previous partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With By the time John was 40, his oil company owned 90% of the world’s oil refining industry. At this point, Standard oil has not simply become a national monopoly, but rather an international one. This was only possible with the use of immoral business tactics (which can be read in more detail on Wikipedia), which were ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1911, the supreme court of the US declared that Standard Oil was a monopoly. This one big company was divided into 34 separate entities (famous descendants alive today are Chevron Corp, ExxonMobil, and BP), hence making room for competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockefeller kept his stake in all of those companies, and the companies’ combined net worth ended up making him even richer than before. By the end of his lifetime, this man was worth between 300-400B (accounted for inflation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;quotes-by-john-d-rockefeller&quot;&gt;Quotes by John D. Rockefeller&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I don’t want a nation of thinkers, I want a nation of workers”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Her judgment was always better than mine. Without her keen advice, I would be a poor man”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Andrei Guevorkian</name></author><category term="Business" /><summary type="html">John D. Rockefeller was born in 1839 in NYC. His father was of English and German descent and his mother was of Scots-Irish descent. When people speak of the Rockefellers, it’s because of John. John D. Rockefeller not only built an empire, but he did so with humble beginnings.</summary></entry></feed>